<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A voyage of the Sieur Le Maire to the Canary Islands, Cape-Verd, Senegal and Gamby, under Monsieur Dancourt, Director-General of the Royal African Company Printed at Paris this present year 1695. And now faithfully done into English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 161 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96033</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V741A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230540</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896042</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896042</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153719</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96033)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153719)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2375:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A voyage of the Sieur Le Maire to the Canary Islands, Cape-Verd, Senegal and Gamby, under Monsieur Dancourt, Director-General of the Royal African Company Printed at Paris this present year 1695. And now faithfully done into English.</title>
                  <author>Le Maire, Jacques-Joseph.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>135, [5] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for F. Mills and W. Turner, at the Rose and C[r]own without Temple-Bar,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The "r" in "Crown" failed to print in the imprint.</note>
                  <note>Last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C..</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Voyages and travels --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>East Indies --  Description and travel --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Africa, West --  Description and travel --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153719:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153719:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153719:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153719:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153719:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153719:3"/>
            <p>A VOYAGE OF THE Sieur <hi>Le Maire</hi> TO THE <hi>Canary Iſlands, Cape-Verd, Senegal</hi> and <hi>Gamby,</hi> UNDER Monſieur DANCOURT, Director-General of the Royal <hi>Affrican</hi> Company.</p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>Paris</hi> this Preſent Year 1695.</p>
            <p>And now faithfully done into <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>F. Mills</hi> and <hi>W. Turner,</hi> at the <hi>Roſe and C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>own</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar.</hi> 1696.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:153719:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153719:4"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>IT is now a conſiderable time, ſince this Relation was put into my Hands by my very good Friend the Sieur <hi>Le Maire,</hi> upon his return from the Voyage which he perform'd into thoſe Countries, whereof he has given us a Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>The Reading of it ſeem'd ſo diverting, and the Account ſo ſingular, that at first ſight it appear'd to me not a little ſuſpected, ſince it differs in many Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial things from an Author of this Age, in a Collection which he has made Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:153719:5"/>
            <p>Theſe Important Contradictions, made me reſolve to be ſatisfied of the Truth, by thoſe who accompanied my Friend in his Travels: I made it my buſineſs to have particular Conferences with each of them, eſpecially upon thoſe Heads which ſeem'd ſo oppoſite in theſe different Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations; and I found them ſo correſpond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Matters of Fact, which crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted my Scruples, that I believ'd I could not better repair the Injuſtice I had done my Friend, than by revoking my Doubts, and repoſing a Confidence in him, which till then I had ſuſpended.</p>
            <p>Monſieur <hi>Dancourt,</hi> Director-General of the <hi>Affrican</hi> Company, under whom my Friend made this Voyage, who has acquir'd a perfect knowledge of the Lives and Manners of the Inhabitants of theſe Iſlands, and of the Curioſities of theſe Countries, by his long Travels, almoſt through all the Parts of the World; (which has procur'd him the Eſteem of the Meſſieurs <hi>Colbert</hi> and <hi>Soignelay</hi>) the Conferences (I ſay) which I had with
<pb facs="tcp:153719:5"/>him, did not a little contribute to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min in favour of this latter Relation, which he found to be very exact, and that the Author had enter'd into Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularities, which till now were never touch'd upon by any Perſon whatever.</p>
            <p>My Friends, who had look'd it over, concluded that I had injur'd the Publick in concealing this Novelty ſo long, and did at length perſwade me to alter my Reſolution of not Publiſhing this Piece till the return of the Author, who would, no doubt, have made a conſiderable Addition of new Remarks. But ſince 'tis four or five Years ſince I heard any thing of him, I thought I ſhould do him no wrong in Publiſhing the Fruits of his firſt Voyages, which may beſpeak a good Reception of what he himſelf ſhall think fit to give us for the future; and, perhaps, the Applauſe of this Work may the ſooner engage him to Publiſh his Remarks of his later Travels.</p>
            <p>Indeed, the Induſtrious Care which the Author has taken to penetrate into the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, of the Manners, Religion, and
<pb facs="tcp:153719:6"/>Politicks, of the People, who Inhabit the Coaſts of <hi>Affrica,</hi> does very well merit an Univerſal Approbation.</p>
            <p>One may take a view here of their Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal, of the Tyranny which the Kings ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe ever their Subjects and Neighbours, of many Petty Kings Tributary to each other, their Policy, and their manner of making War.</p>
            <p>One may find here the perfidious Deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of theſe People towards the <hi>Europeans</hi> in reſpect of their Traffick; the Fertility of a Country that is in no manner Cultivated; their Miſeries for want of Induſtry and Forecaſt; what Animals are common in this Climate; And, in ſhort, all things that are the moſt Remarkable in theſe Iſlands, and not to be met withal in other Places.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:153719:6"/>
            <head>THE VOYAGES OF THE Sieur <hi>Le Maire</hi> TO THE <hi>Canaries, Cape-Verd, Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal,</hi> and <hi>Gamby.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I Had ſerv'd in the Capacity of Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeon to the <hi>Hotel-Dieu</hi> of <hi>Paris</hi> near the ſpace of three Years, when I receiv'd intimation, that Monſieur <hi>Dancourt</hi> was ready to ſet forwards for <hi>Cape-Verd,</hi> as General Director of the Royal <hi>Affrican</hi> Company. This News created a Deſire in me to make the Voyage along with him. He ſeem'd glad at the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153719:7"/>opportunity of my Company, and after having determin'd our Agreement, he Preſented me to the Members of that So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety on the 14th of <hi>January</hi> 1682. who readily ratified the Articles we had before concluded.</p>
            <p>After having ſpent ſome time in ſettling my Affairs, and taking leave of my Friends, we departed for <hi>Orleans,</hi> where we took a Boat to go to <hi>Nantes</hi> along the <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> We ought not in courſe to have been more than three days in accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Journey; however, it took us up ſeven or eight entirely, beſides running of great riſques, and expoſing our ſelves to many dangers.</p>
            <p>We had the Wind all along full in our Teeth, and ſo ſtrong a Gale, that the Waves of this River did near equal the toſſings of the Sea: To this inconveniency was added that of the Banks being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow'd, ſo that we ſeldom was ſenſible whether we were in, or off the Chanel. We could only diſcern ſome ſtraggling branches above Water, ſo that we ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times fell foul upon the Trunks of Trees where Birds do build their Neſts.</p>
            <p>However, at length we arriv'd at <hi>Nantes,</hi> and after having reſted there for
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153719:7"/>the ſpace of ten days, we took Horſe for <hi>Breſt.</hi> What we ſaw of <hi>Brettagny</hi> as we rode along, afforded no very pleaſant Idea, had we not already been otherways inform'd, that it was a Province rich and fertile in ſome places, ſince the whole Journey gave us no other proſpect but of a Sandy Road, which occaſion'd very tedious Travelling.</p>
            <p>Having reach'd <hi>Breſt</hi> the 4th of <hi>Februa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> we believ'd we ſhould Sail in few days; but the Veſſel was not yet in a condition, ſhe being but indifferently fitted out, and very defective in her Rigging. We were to wait till ſhe was new Maſted, and put in a capacity to bear Weather, and to Fight too if there were occaſion.</p>
            <p>Two Months was ſpent in refitting this Ship, which was call'd the <hi>St. Catharine;</hi> ſhe was of 400 Tun burthen, and carried 40 Guns: She was built at <hi>Fluſhing,</hi> and deſign'd for a quick Sailor, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by Captain <hi>Monſegur,</hi> by the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Members of this Company.</p>
            <p>The Port of <hi>Breſt,</hi> where ſhe then was, is by much the beſt Harbour we have in the Ocean; the largeſt Veſſels Ride there in ſafety, and lye as it were in a Chamber ſheltred from all manner of prejudice from
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153719:8"/>the bluſtring Winds, for which reaſon it has receiv'd that Name; they can go out to Sea as well at low Water as at high Tide, ſince the Ships there always ride a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>float: Its Entrance is as narrow as the Mouth of a River, fortified of each ſide with two good Half-Moons, and on the Right has a ſtately Caſtle of Antick Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to defend the Paſſage. This Haven ſhoots up in a Spiral Line; it is a large half League in length, and about 200 Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces over, ſituated between two Hills: All which Advantages are the pure effects of Nature.</p>
            <p>I ſaw in this Port the fineſt and largeſt Ships in the whole World; amongſt the reſt, the Admiral call'd the <hi>Royal Sun,</hi> ſhe is not ſo richly Gilt as the <hi>Royal Lewis of Thoulon,</hi> but ſhe is better Built, of a greater length, and a more nimble Sailor. She carries a Hundred and Twenty Pieces of Cannon, and fortified with three Decks; her State-Room is Magnificent, curiouſly Gilt and Beautified; her Plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form was deſign'd by Monſieur <hi>Le Brun,</hi> ſhe has about 15 more Apartments, but much leſs; however they are very conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient and handſom.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:153719:8"/>
            <p>Beſides this Veſſel, there were more than fifty other Ships, of 90, of 80, 70, 60, 50 Guns each, without taking notice of thoſe of lower Rates. Next to the <hi>Royal Sun,</hi> the fineſt are, The <hi>Queen,</hi> the <hi>Crown,</hi> the <hi>Glorious,</hi> the <hi>Brave,</hi> the <hi>Good,</hi> the <hi>Thundring,</hi> the <hi>Lightning,</hi> the <hi>Rock,</hi> and the <hi>Diamond,</hi> &amp;c. The proſpect of thoſe vaſt Machines, like ſo many floating Palaces, appears delightfully aſtoniſhing; nor can they be view'd without exciting a Veneration of the Puiſſance of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Maſter.</p>
            <p>Our Veſſel being Rigg'd and Fitted, it fell down into the Road on the 20th of <hi>March:</hi> Five of the King's Ships, well appointed, went out at the ſame time, four of which was to join the Fleet of <hi>Thoulon,</hi> in the Expedition againſt the <hi>Algiers,</hi> and the other was to Convoy ſome Ships belonging to the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wedneſday</hi> the 9th of <hi>April</hi> 1682. I em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bark'd with four more of the Family that were to go along with us, Monſieur <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>court</hi> ſtaying yet at <hi>Breſt.</hi> In the mean while, theſe Gentlemen and I made a Match of Shooting, imagining it was as eaſie to come on Board again as it was to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153719:9"/>go off. The Director's Cook was brought aboard about ſome buſineſs, in a little Skiff Row'd by two Young Lads of about eleven or twelve Years each.</p>
            <p>The opportunity ſeem'd lucky for us, and we, without conſidering how we ſhould get back again, took his Boat, and went almoſt two Leagues off near to <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maret;</hi> the eager deſire of our Sport, made us Land at the firſt place we came to, ſlighting the danger of climbing the Rocks that hung ſhelving over the Sea, from which I was near falling two or three ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times.</p>
            <p>After all our pains, we had not the good Fortune to meet with any ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Game, but were oblig'd to take up with killing a few Larks, which at length ſtood us in more ſtead than we imagin'd. We left our unlucky Sport, and ſet to a better, refreſhing our ſelves with ſome good Wine and cold Proviſions we had with us.</p>
            <p>When we had conſum'd what Stock we had, we went aboard our ſmall Skiff, and had ſcarce got off to Sea, when a violent Storm aroſe, which ſoon put me to my Devotions, imagining that we ſhould un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidably periſh in a moment. One of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153719:9"/>our Companions being exceſſively tir'd, fell faſt aſleep at his firſt getting into the Boat, but being at length diſturb'd with our frequent ſhricks, when we were got near half way to our Veſſel, he, though not wholly awake, began to perceive the danger, and cry'd out that we ſhould cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be loſt, if we did not return aſhore with what ſpeed was poſſible.</p>
            <p>This Opinion ſeem'd to us very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, ſince the ſtrength of our Young Water-men was very inconſiderable, tho' they ſhew'd much greater courage than any of us, telling us, That the Boat would only over-turn, and that there was no danger of its ſinking to the bottom. I ſuppoſe they imagin'd that all of us could Swim; but indeed they were miſtaken, for I very well knew my own Ability. Sometimes I entertain'd my thoughts with the difficulty of eſcaping amongſt Waves that were ſo large and violent, which I concluded would infallibly daſh us in pieces againſt the Rocks.</p>
            <p>We readily embrac'd the Advice of our Comrade, and ſet all hands to Work to Row back to ſhore, and with much labour we gain'd the Land, to wait there till the Storm was abated.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:153719:10"/>
            <p>Whilſt each of us was reliſhing a ſmall Tranquillity, we heard the report of a Cannon, and at the ſame time ſaw the Top-ſail loos'd, which is the ordinary Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal for Sailing. There were ſome Lighters at hand, but we could by no means find the Maſters that own'd them to carry us on Board.</p>
            <p>Thus we ſaw our Ship under Sail, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luting the Admiral with ſeven Guns, the Wind full a Stern, all the Sails out, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hopes of regaining her. I look'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my ſelf to be in a miſerable taking, without Cloaths, without Inſtruments, and expos'd to the Extremities of Fortune.</p>
            <p>We follow'd the ſight of our Veſſel, tearing our Throats, and firing our Fuzees, but to no purpoſe, ſhe in a little time diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appear'd. One of our Comrades not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo good of Foot as the reſt, took the way to <hi>Camaret,</hi> believing he ſhould find us there; for our parts we were looking after him; ſo we ſpent the beſt part of the Night ſeeking each other.</p>
            <p>Thouſands of Unfortunate Accidents befel us, one ſtuck in a Bog, the other fell into a Ditch, and each call'd out upon the other for aſſiſtance, and Curſing our Sport was the common Dialect of us all.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:153719:10"/>Hunger came in the Rear of our other Misfortunes. We at length took into a ſmall Hedge-Tavern, where, by good luck, every thing was anſwerable to the ſmall Stock we had to ſpend.</p>
            <p>We met with nothing there but a Cruſt of very brown Bread, a Scrap of <hi>Holland</hi>-Cheeſe, and Straw Beds; the ſmall Stock of Money we had was expended for diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging our Supper and Lodging; and for our Breakfaſt, we deferr'd it to a more favourable opportunity.</p>
            <p>Whilſt we were upon the hunt for our ſtraggling Companion, Coaſting the Sea, we diſcover'd ſome Maſts, which we at firſt took for Trees that grew upon the Banks of the River, not daring to flatter our ſelves that we ſhould ever regain the ſight of a Veſſel, which we at that time imagin'd to be far diſtant from us; but drawing nearer, we perceiv'd that ſhe was not gone, and that ſhe lay at Anchor in the Road of <hi>Camaret,</hi> three Leagues from <hi>Breſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You may eaſily imagine our Joy, there was nothing now to be done but to find our loſt Comrade, and ſo go on Board. We endeavour'd to make Signs to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the Ship that they might know us,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:153719:11"/>and ſend off their Shalop, but we were no more ſucceſsful in this than in our former Enterpriſes.</p>
            <p>Whilſt we were contriving all manner of ways to get out of this Scrape, we perceiv'd a ſmall Bark, which hir'd her ſelf to carry off to any Veſſels at Sea. I can't tell how it came to paſs that our ſtray'd Comrade ſhould be there; but ſo it was, he was the firſt that knew us. We made ſigns to him, he underſtood us, and order'd the Bark to come near us; but though the ſhore was almoſt unacceſſible, upon the account of the Rocks, yet we were oblig'd to get aboard in ſpight of all their threatning Precipices.</p>
            <p>At length we got in, and after many Congratulations of being once again met together, we ſettled our ſelves to repoſe: But it ſeems it was not yet time to take our eaſe, for the Waves roſe ſo high, that they waſh'd over the Boat from Head to Stern; ſo that we were all throughly Sous'd. This, together with the Cold that it oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion'd, and the danger of being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, which our Seamen ſeem'd to dread, renew'd our Miſeries, till at laſt, after theſe unlucky Adventures, we arriv'd ſafe aboard.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:153719:11"/>
            <p>We laugh'd at leiſure at all theſe Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, and ſet immediately to remedy our preſent Hunger: We lay ſometime longer in the Road to wait for Monſieur <hi>Dancourt,</hi> who ſtaid at <hi>Breſt.</hi> He arriv'd <hi>Sunday</hi> the 12th of <hi>April</hi> 1682. about Noon, and we immediately made ready to Sail.</p>
            <p>About three Leagues off at Sea, we met with the Ship call'd the <hi>Burning;</hi> ſhe Rode at Anchor waiting for the Tide to carry her into the Bay of <hi>Breſt,</hi> ſhe carried to Guns, and came from <hi>Haver</hi> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> aboard Monſieur <hi>de Preuilly</hi> the Lieutenant General, and was afterwards to Sail with him for the Coaſt of <hi>Algier.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſaluted her after the accuſtom'd manner, with ſeven Guns, Trumpets Sounding, and crying three times, <hi>Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e le Roy.</hi> She return'd as many, contrary to the General practice of the King's Ships, who always give two leſs. It ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd that it was out of Complaiſance to the <hi>Intendant,</hi> who was an intimate Friend of Monſieur <hi>Dancourts,</hi> and then aboard her.</p>
            <p>Having return'd our thanks with three Guns, we continued our Courſe, the Wind being at North Eaſt, having doubled the Cape to the Weſt, making Weſt South
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:153719:12"/>Weſt, from whence we took our Point to Steer, at 48 degrees 20 Minutes of the Northern Latitude, and 11 degrees of Longitude. But ſince I am not very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port in the buſineſs of Pilotage, I ſhall not for the future make any ſuch particular re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cites, unleſs they be abſolutely neceſſary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tueſday,</hi> the 21th of <hi>April,</hi> we made two Veſſels direct Eaſt of us; by their endeavours to get the Wind of us, we indg'd them to be <hi>Pirates.</hi> We put our ſelves in a poſture of Defence, which no doubt prevented their coming upon us, they gueſſing by our Countenance that they could expect from us nothing but dry Blows.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sunday,</hi> the 26th in the Morning, we were in 32 Degrees and as many Minutes of the Northern Latitude, and in 4 De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees 13 Minutes of Longitude, when we made the <hi>Cape Cautin,</hi> the Coaſts of <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bary,</hi> and the Kingdom of <hi>Morocco,</hi> being but ſix Leagues from Land. Had the Night continued we had certainly periſh'd, ſince we took our Courſe for the Weſt of <hi>Madera,</hi> which was above 140 Leagues from thence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> the 29th, we made the Iſland of <hi>Ancerott,</hi> one of the Seven <hi>Canaries,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:153719:12"/>which we left about 10 Leagues to the South-Eaſt; here we were for ſome time becalm'd, and ſuffer'd the ſcorching of exceſſive heats.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thurſday,</hi> the 30th of <hi>April,</hi> we were got in 28 Degrees and 30 Minutes Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Latitude, taking, according to the Cuſtom of our Nation, the firſt Meridian from the Iſland of <hi>Fer,</hi> having then the <hi>Grand Canary</hi> 10 Leagues from us to the North-Eaſt. We went off a Fowling near a League into the Iſland, where we ſtaid till Night. We could not come to an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor for want of a Wind, and for the darkneſs of the Night which came on, which made us ſtand off to the Eaſt, and continue till three hours after Midnight oppoſite to Land.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Friday,</hi> by break of day, we veer'd to the Weſtward, taking our Courſe to the <hi>Great Canary:</hi> About half an hour after Nine we came to an Anchor in 24 Fathom Water, and brought up a gray and red Sand mix'd with Coral; the Town which lay South South-Weſt, is a League and half from the Road, and is defended by a Caſtie, though very mean and deſpicable.</p>
            <p>When they perceiv'd us from off the Caſtle, they hoiſted the Flag of <hi>Spain,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:153719:13"/>which we Saluted with five Guns; but they made no return, which I believe was occaſion'd by want of Powder.</p>
            <p>Anchorage is extream good in this place, ſo that they don't draw too near the Town, whoſe approach is render'd dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous by Rocks that lye conceal'd under Water. It is Guarded by a Caſtle ſituated upon a Hill, from the Inſults it might ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer by any Veſſels that might undertake to Attack it. 'Tis Inhabited by Twelve Thouſand flout Iſlanders, who are capable of making a very good Defence. Our Ship Anchor'd before the Town in 18 Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thom Water.</p>
            <p>Its Precincts are near a League in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, moſt of the Houſes well built, but low, having not above two Stories, they are all flat Roord, ſo that no Ridge ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, and one would be apt to take them for Houſes ſo far burnt down. In the day time, ſcarce any Body appears in the Streets.</p>
            <p>Though the Biſhop, the Governor, and the Men of Quality, make their Reſidence at <hi>Teneriff,</hi> yet the See Epiſcopal, the Tribunal of the Inquiſition, and the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Council, which is, as it were, the Parliament of the ſeven Iſlands, are always
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:153719:13"/>kept in this Capital. There is here four Religious Foundations, one belonging to the <hi>Dominicans,</hi> one to the <hi>Franciſcons;</hi> the two other are the <hi>Bernardins</hi> and the <hi>Recollects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Iſlands, who heretofore were call'd the <hi>Fortunate,</hi> had that Title not without good Reaſon, if we conſider ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Goodneſs and Purity of the Air, or the Fertility of the Soil. They abound in Bread-Corn, Barley, Honey, Beef, Mutton, Fowl; in ſhort, with all Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries for good and plentiful Living. They afford ſo large a Store of <hi>Malmſy</hi> Sack, that <hi>France, Spain, England, Holland,</hi> and other places, are from thence furniſh'd every Year.</p>
            <p>The felicity that theſe Iſlands are capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of beſtowing above any others, in what reſpects commodious Living, gave, ſome time ſince, occaſion to the Pagans belief. That theſe were the <hi>Elizian</hi> Fields, deſtin'd for the Habitation of the Souls of the Bleſſed, after their ſeparation from the Body.</p>
            <p>Their Water is not proportionably good with the reſt of their Commodities, but they have a way to remedy it, by pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it into Veſſels made in the ſhape of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:153719:14"/>Mortars, of a Stone very Poroſe, through which being ſtrain'd, it becomes freſh and purified, and conſequently very wholſom.</p>
            <p>Their Harveſt is commonly in <hi>March,</hi> ſometimes in <hi>April,</hi> and in ſeveral places they are double in each Year: The Soil is ſo Redundant, that I have ſeen a Cheriy Tree Slip produce Fruit in 6 Weeks time after it had been Grafted. Flowers thrive there without requiring any manner of Induſtry; and Oranges, and Citrons, are in a ſurpriſing Plenty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Grand Canary,</hi> as well as <hi>Teneriff,</hi> and the <hi>Palme,</hi> did continue ſome time in Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try after the Conqueſt of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> made in 1460. <hi>Ancerott, Fort-Avanture, Gomere</hi> and <hi>Fer,</hi> did firſt eſpouſe Chriſtianity, and at length the other three follow'd their example. The <hi>Spaniards</hi> deſiring abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to reduce this Country to their Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, ſent great ſtore of the Inhabitants Slaves into <hi>Spain;</hi> thoſe that remain'd amongſt them became Civiliz'd, and liv'd after the manner of their Conquerors Theſe People, eſpecially thoſe of <hi>Grand Canary,</hi> are extream Lovers of Strangers.</p>
            <p>Monſieur <hi>Dancourt</hi> was very Honourably receiv'd by the Governor of the Iſland, at whoſe Houſe he was entertain'd at Dinner,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:153719:14"/>being conducted by Monſieur <hi>Remond</hi> Conſul of our Nation, who was Born at <hi>Liege,</hi> and is a very honeſt Courteous Gentleman. He Regal'd us very Nobly, and let us want for neither Liquor nor Fruit; I ſtaid two entire days with him, where I receiv'd all the Civilities imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable.</p>
            <p>I was four times at the Convent of <hi>Bernardins,</hi> the Providore having given me that permiſſion at the Inſtance of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Abbeſs. There were here ſome <hi>French</hi> Ladies, amongſt the reſt one from <hi>Paris,</hi> who did me the kind Service of being my Interpreter. As there were ſome amongſt them that were Infirm, they omitted not the opportunity of Adviſing with me, and of giving me great Reſpect and Attention</p>
            <p>A Phyſician being at hand, made ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of them make the beſt of the opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and many of them complain'd that had no real occaſion, hoping thereby to gain the greater liberty, tho' otherwiſe they were no how indiſpos'd. I ſoon diſcover'd, that the greateſt part of them had no other Diſtemper, but of that of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lock'd up from the reſt of the World, and therefore I could furniſh them with no Effectual Cure. However, to appear a
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:153719:15"/>Perſon ſomething conſiderable, and of Univerſal Experience, I order'd them ſome Specifick Medicines, ſuch as was moſt proper for Chimetical Diſtempers.</p>
            <p>Theſe good Religious Ladies were not wanting in their Careſſes, and took care to load me with Biskets, dry and wet Sweet-meats, Lemonade, and Sack; to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with all manner of Fruit, which they had ſerv'd up upon Plates, and Porcelain Salvers, garniſh'd with Roſes, Pinks, Orange-Flowers, Jeſſimin, and Tuberoſes, with variety of Noſegays. I alſo made them ſome ſmall Preſents, which were receiv'd with great Reſpect and Civility.</p>
            <p>When I left theſe good Ladies, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd to the Conſul's, there were more People that waited, to take me along with them to Viſit the Sick. Particularly, I went to a certain Lawyer's eſteem'd worth Five hundred thouſand Crowns, whoſe Wife had long labour'd with the Suffocation of the Womb, which was caus'd by ſome Obſtructions: The Doctors of the Place dealt with her as a <hi>Peripneumony,</hi> by which chiefly I diſcover'd their Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:153719:15"/>
            <p>Their general diſtruſt of them, makes the Inhabitants very fond of any <hi>French</hi> Chirurgeons. The Lawyer us'd his utmoſt endeavours to perſwade me to take up my Abode in the <hi>Grand Canary,</hi> offering me his Houſe, and his Table, and great Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages beſides. I had no mind to forfeit the promiſe I made to Monſieur <hi>Dancourt,</hi> ſo that I made my returns of Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgments for the obliging offers of the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> and preſcrib'd what Remedies I thought moſt proper for his Lady, and what might be beſt met withal in the Iſland; where, indeed, Medicines are very ſcarce.</p>
            <p>He offer'd me a Recompence in Money, which, out of Honour for our Nation, I wholly refus'd. I had deſign'd to have viſited him again in a day or two, ſince he had begg'd that favour of the <hi>Conſul,</hi> adding, that he would find out ſome other way of gratifying me, ſince I refus'd his firſt offer; but I had not time, the Boat being come to fetch me on Board the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turday</hi> Evening.</p>
            <p>I do aſſure you, I was almoſt Enchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Sweetneſs of that Country; ſo that I could ſcarce leave it without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret. Should I ever quit <hi>France,</hi> it ſhould
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:153719:16"/>be to fix my Habitation in the <hi>Grand Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary,</hi> though I hope I ſhall never be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd wholly to leave my own Country, which I muſt own is very dear to me. Before I have done with this Iſland, I muſt not forget to acquaint you, that it is about 30 Leagues in Compaſs, and of a Form very near Round.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saturday,</hi> the 2d of <hi>May,</hi> in the Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the Wind being North North Eaſt, we made ready about Three a Clock in the Morning; we took our Courſe in the ſight of the <hi>Pique,</hi> a high Mountain in the Iſland of <hi>Teneriff,</hi> and made forwards to Ride in the Road of St. <hi>Cruce.</hi> Our Pilot obſerv'd in this place, that the Compaſs varied to the North Eaſt 3 Degrees, and 30 Minutes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sunday,</hi> the 3d, being full North of the <hi>Grand Canary,</hi> having a gentle Breeze at North North Eaſt, we lay off Weſtward from the Cape all Night.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Monday,</hi> the 4th, in the Morning, we arriv'd at <hi>Teneriff,</hi> the Richeſt of all the <hi>Canaries,</hi> being in ſight of <hi>St. Cruce,</hi> a ſmall Town of the ſame Iſland, upon its Eaſtern Point. We might there have Anchor'd in 25, or 30 Fathom Water; in the mean while we
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:153719:16"/>never drop'd our Anchor, but our Ship lay by all the time, expecting the return of our Shalop, which we ſent aſhore.</p>
            <p>Though the Governor of <hi>St. Cruce</hi> ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd thoſe that were in the Boat to come aſhore, yet he ſent to acquaint the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor-General, who had his Reſidence at <hi>Laguna,</hi> 3 Leagues from the Sea-ſide, that there were ſome <hi>French</hi> who deſir'd to come on Shore to take in ſome Proviſions, which they ſtood in need of: Whoſe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer was, That he ſhould detain them if they did it. Perhaps he fear'd that we had ſome Infection on Board, ſhould we have come from the <hi>Levant,</hi> a place very ſubject to Contagion.</p>
            <p>To what remains when I ſpeak of the <hi>Pique,</hi> I muſt acquaint you by the by, that it is one of the higheſt Mountains in the World. 'Tis ſaid that it may be ſeen 40 Leagues off at Sea; as for us, we m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it not above 12 or 15, by reaſon of the Duskineſs of the Evening, which made it appear to us like a Pointed Cloud; 'tis continually cover'd with Snow, which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther falls off, nor does it ever Freeze.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Teneriff,</hi> it is reputed to lye the higheſt of any Iſland in the Ocean, and the beſt Peopled for its bigneſs, containing
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:153719:17"/>about 15000 Inhabitants: She produces that Excellent <hi>Malmſey</hi> Sack, which, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Conteſt, is eſteem'd the beſt in the World. This Liquor was not known in this Iſland, till after the <hi>Spaniards</hi> had made themſelves Maſters of it, ſince they were the firſt that tranſplanted ſome Vine-Stocks from <hi>Candy;</hi> though, at this day, the Wine is juſtly allow'd a preference to that from whence it owes its Original, and a much larger quantity of it is here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd than in <hi>Candy</hi> it ſelf.</p>
            <p>All the ſeven Iſlands of the <hi>Canaries</hi> lye almoſt in a direct Line from Eaſt to Weſt, they are very Mountainous, well Peopled, and extraordinary Fertil; the leaſt of which is 60 Miles in Compaſs.</p>
            <p>I had formerly heard Diſcourſe of a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous Tree in the Iſland of <hi>Fer,</hi> whoſe Leaves were long and narrow, always green, which ſupply'd the Inhabitants with all their Water. I had a mind to inform my ſelf of the Truth of it, I therefore ask'd concerning it, whether ſo great a Dew fix'd it ſelf on this Plant, that it continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally diſtill'd a clear and wholſom Water into Baſons of Stone ſet on purpoſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it; ſo that there would be, by this means, a ſufficient quantity both for the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:153719:17"/>Inhabitants and their Cattel, Nature kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſupplying, by this perpetual Miracle, the want of freſh Water, which was not to be met withal throughout the whole Iſland. The Inhabitants confirm'd me in the Opinion that I had before entertain'd, that it was a meer Fable. There were, however, ſome that told me, that there was ſuch a ſort of Trees, but that they never furniſh'd ſuch prodigious quantity of Water which was ſpoke of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tueſday,</hi> the 5th, we continued our Courſe to the South, being in 27 Degrees 40 Minutes Northern Latitude, and in 360 Degrees Eaſtern Longitude. About Six a Clock in the Evening, being full South off the <hi>Grand Canary,</hi> we kept Eaſt North Eaſt for about 7 Leagues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> the 6th, it blew ſo ſtrong an Eaſterly Wind, that the Tackling of the Top-Sail, and the Main-Yard, broke in pieces, and the Main-Maſt buckled ſo much, that it was in danger of breaking. This Wind ceas'd in a quarter of an hour, afterwards, and the Veſſel began to be Steady and Trim.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thurſday,</hi> the 7th, at Noon, being in 20 Degrees Northern Latitude, and in 28 Minutes <hi>Eaſter.</hi> Longitude, we cut the <hi>Tropick</hi> of <hi>Cancer.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:153719:18"/>
            <p>It was not forgot in this place, to keep up the Ceremony that is us'd by all Sailors, they call it the Baptiſm; 'tis put in practice upon all thoſe who never yet paſs'd the <hi>Tropick.</hi> See here the whole Deſcription of it. They ſet a great Tub of Water at the foot of the Main-Maſt, with a Stick laid a-croſs it; Then thoſe, that have been Initiated in former Voyages, having Grim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>c'd their Faces with Smut, walk in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion a-round the Deck, one carrying a drawn Cut-laſh, another a Frying-Pan, and the reſt ſeveral of the Kitchen Uten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſils. The Pilot, to diſtinguiſh himſelf, turns his Coat, and Diſplays ſome tatter'd Rag inſtead of a pair of Colours. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion being finiſh'd, which is always per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd in great State, with Trumpets Sounding, and Drums Beating, they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to Baptizing of the Ship, flinging ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Peals of Water about the Deck, till the Captain gives the Ship's Crew ſome Drink-Money.</p>
            <p>They go then, firſt, to the moſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable of the Ship, whom they make to ſit, one after the other, upon the Stick I already mention'd: The Mob gets about. him, preſenting a Baſon to receive his Baptiſmal Offering, holding the Cymeter
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:153719:18"/>a croſs his Neck: Then the Pilot brings his Book of Charts, and makes the Patient put his Hand upon the <hi>Tropick</hi> Line, and Swear to obſerve this Ceremony, in like manner, at any time for the future, to thoſe that were freſh Travellers. At length they mark him with a black <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>s upon the Forehead, and fling a little Water up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Head, which follow'd by a Preſent flung into the Baſon, they diſmiſs him; tho', if it be a Perſon of Common Rank, they draw the Stick from under him, Souſing him into the Tub, flinging Buckets of Water upon him, and thumping him, at a good Rate, with the Stick he ſat up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. There is a neceſſity of undergoing this Ceremony, nor is an Admiral himſelf exempted, though they uſe him in a more Civil manner than ordinary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Friday,</hi> the 8th, we drew near the Coaſt of <hi>Barbary,</hi> being at Mid-day in 21 De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees 47 Minutes Northern Latitude, the Wind blowing a freſh Gale at North North Eaſt, we were ſatisfied that it was impoſſible to reach <hi>Cape-Blanc</hi> within Day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, being 4 Leagues off from Land, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving 28 Fathom Water, with a Sandy bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom; we kept our bent Eaſt South Eaſt, and on <hi>Saturday</hi> the 9th, about Eight a
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:153719:19"/>Clock in the Morning, we found our ſelves but a League from ſhore.</p>
            <p>We Coaſted along to <hi>Cape-Blanc,</hi> and Anchor'd there in 14 fathom Water to the North-Weſt, being about a League from the Point of the Cape; which is, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our Account, in 20 Degrees 30 Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes Northern Latitude, and 359 Degrees 10 Minutes Weſtern Longitude.</p>
            <p>When the <hi>Portugueſe</hi> diſcover'd this Cape, about the Year 1454. they gave it the Name of <hi>Cape-Blanc,</hi> by reaſon of its bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren white Sand, inſomuch that nothing of Green appears in view. It lies almoſt as flat as the Sea; on which Account 'tis call'd the <hi>Sea of Sand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From <hi>Cape-Cantin</hi> to this place, which is 300 Leagues, nothing is to be ſeen but a Flat of Sand, by the Ancients call'd, <hi>The Deſart of Lybia,</hi> and by the Arabians <hi>Zaara.</hi> It's not Inhabited, ſave only with Wild Beaſts, ſuch as <hi>Lions, Tygers, Ounces, Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pards,</hi> and other like ſort of Creatures.</p>
            <p>Theſe Deſarts are bounded on the North by <hi>Mount Atlas,</hi> and to the South by the Country of the <hi>Negers;</hi> they are of that extent from Eaſt to Weſt, that they can't be croſs'd on Horſeback under the ſpace of 50 days. Over theſe Sands, the Caravans
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:153719:19"/>paſs from <hi>Fez</hi> to <hi>Tombut, Melly, Borneo,</hi> and other Kingdoms of the <hi>Negers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When any Storm ariſes in theſe Deſarts, the Sands overwhelm both the Paſſengers and their Camels, often ſmothering them to Death; at other times, filling up the ſtanding Pits of Water, ſo that they periſh by Thirſt. The <hi>Caravans,</hi> for want of any beaten Track, are oblig'd to make uſe of the Compaſs as tho' they were at Sea.</p>
            <p>At the Point of <hi>Cape-Blanc,</hi> there is form'd a certain Gulf which takes its Name from the Iſland which it makes, and is call'd <hi>Arguin.</hi> This Gulf ſhoots up more than 15 Leagues within Land, by which the proſpect of it is loſt having once paſs'd the Point.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Portugueſe</hi> had formerly a Fort in this Iſland, where they Eſtabliſh'd a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce with the <hi>Azoaghes, Arabs,</hi> or <hi>Moors,</hi> who Traffick'd with them for Gold, Gum-Arabick, Oſtridges Plumes, which are there in great Plenty, by reaſon of the abundance of thoſe Birds. 'Tis ſaid-of this Animal, that they are ſo far deſtitute of Memory, that they forget where they lay their Eggs, and that they brood over the firſt they chance to meet withal. I much doubted the Truth of the Report,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:153719:20"/>that one of theſe Eggs were ſufficient to ſatisfie the Appetite of eight Men of good Stomach. To the reſt, they bring theſe Merchandiſes from <hi>Hoden,</hi> which is four days Journey into the Main Land, and is the place where the <hi>Caravans</hi> arrive from <hi>Tombut, Gualata,</hi> and other Inland places of <hi>Lybia,</hi> and the Country of the <hi>Negers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe People are Diſciples of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> they never continue long ſettled in a place, but wander in the Deſarts from one part to another, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as they meet with Paſturage for their Horſes, Camels, Cattel, Sheep, and Goats, by whoſe Milk they are nouriſhed. They are divided into Tribes or Lineages, they own no King or Superior by any legal Right, though he that has the greateſt Stock is voluntarily obey'd as their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain or Conductor.</p>
            <p>Their Traffick with the <hi>Negers</hi> conſiſts in Horſes and Camels; they receive for a Horſe, 6, 8, or 10 Slaves, but for a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel only one or two, may be ſometimes three.</p>
            <p>The Fort of <hi>Arguin</hi> was taken by the <hi>Hollanders</hi> from the <hi>Portugueſe,</hi> and taken from them again during the War in 1672. by Monſieur <hi>Ducas,</hi> a Captain of the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:153719:20"/>
               <hi>Affrican</hi> Company. He had but 120 Men in this Expedition, of which he loſt but three. The Supine Negligence of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Governor, contributed much to this eaſie Conqueſt; for there had been nothing more practicable than to have prevented it. Our Artillery conſiſted but of 6 ſmall Pieces, the largeſt being only an 8 Poun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; we had no manner of ſhelter, and above all, we were in great want of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, it being impoſſible to Drink of a ſtink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Spring, which was the only Water our Men could come to in the whole Iſland.</p>
            <p>This Fort was reſerv'd to the <hi>French</hi> by the Peace of <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> with all the other Places that our Company had then in Poſſeſſion. Notwithſtanding which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, the <hi>Hollanders</hi> do every year Traffick thither with ſome of their Veſſels, which is a manifeſt breach of Articles.</p>
            <p>The Captain of our Ship went aſhore with 30 Men, in hopes of finding there the Veſſel call'd the <hi>Town of Hamborough,</hi> but ſhe was already gone off. They met with only one Veſſel upon the Dock, which was not quite finiſh'd, they ſet her on fire, with another ſmall Boat which had on Board ſome <hi>Moors,</hi> and a few <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> who quitted her, and betook them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:153719:21"/>to Swimming. They found her la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with Tortoiſes, which prov'd a good Booty for our Ships Crew, they at that time wanting Proviſions: They are very large upon this Coaſt, and their number in abundance, one alone being able to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate 30 Men; their fleſh very much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembles that of Veal, and reliſhes full as well; their Shells are at leaſt 15 Foot in Circumference.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cape-Blanc</hi> abounds in Fiſh, as <hi>Guiltheads, Pargues, Vielles, Sea-Dogs,</hi> and many other whoſe Names I am not acquainted withal. Our Seamen took great quantities with Angling, and feaſted themſelves highly du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring 8 Days as we Coaſted along the ſhore, till we reach'd the Mouth of the River <hi>Senegal.</hi> There are ſome Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the <hi>Moors,</hi> ſeparated from the reſt, upon this Coaſt, who, through the Baren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Soil, are forc'd to live altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon the Fiſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saturday,</hi> the 7th, we continued our Courſe for <hi>Goree,</hi> and paſs'd in ſight of the River <hi>Senegal;</hi> of which I ſhall Diſcourſe hereafter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tueſday,</hi> the 19th, we made <hi>Cape-Verd,</hi> being in 14 Degrees and 45 Minutes Northern Latitude.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:153719:21"/>
            <p>This Cape was ſo call'd by the <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueſe,</hi> who diſcover'd it the ſame Year as that of <hi>Cape-Blanc</hi> They Nam'd it <hi>Cape-Verd,</hi> becauſe you are immediately pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented with the Proſpect of great Groves of Trees, many of which hold Green all the Year: It lyes high, and affords a moſt raviſhing Proſpect. Above the Woods there appear two round Hills, to which they have given the Name of the <hi>Mammells,</hi> ſince their ſituation do, in ſome meaſure, reſemble a Pair of Breaſts. This Cape juts out a great way into the Ocean, and is eſteem'd the largeſt in the whole Ocean next to that of <hi>Bonne Eſperance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Its ſituation is wrong plac'd in our Charts, where we find it in 14 Degrees exact, though in reality it be 14 Degrees and a half. After having doubled the firſt Point, for there is two, you diſcover a ſmall Iſland which is not Inhabited; 'tis call'd the <hi>Iſland of Birds,</hi> of which, at all times, are ſeen great Flocks, it lying wholly open to view.</p>
            <p>When this Iſland is paſs'd, the other Point muſt be doubled ere you can make <hi>Goree,</hi> which lyes behind the Cape, almoſt oppoſite to the <hi>Mammells.</hi> The Coaſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clines towards the North Weſt, and makes
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:153719:22"/>a Bow, where the beſt Water is to be met withal that is in all theſe Parts, which is a great refreſhment to the Voyagers.</p>
            <p>Being arriv'd at <hi>Goree, Wedneſday</hi> the 20th of <hi>May,</hi> 1682. and Anchor'd in the Road, we Saluted the Fort with 7 Guns; they anſwer'd the Salute, Gun for Gun, the firſt with Shot, out of reſpect to Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Dancourt.</hi> When he went off in his Boat, we Saluted him with 5 Guns; all the Ships that were in the Road did the like, and when he Landed the Fort gave him ſeven.</p>
            <p>After having ſhew'd his Letters from the Company, which conſtituted him Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rector, he enter'd into the Management of his Employ. He found the Affairs in a miſerable Condition, by the ill Conduct of two Perſons, who both pretended to the Soveraign Command: The one was a Frenchman, and Commandant for the Company at <hi>Goree;</hi> the other was their Agent-General all along the Coaſts. But as theſe things are not to my purpoſe, I ſhall ſay nothing farther of theſe Concerns.</p>
            <p>The Iſland of <hi>Goree</hi> was ſo Nam'd by the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> becauſe it reſembles an Iſland in <hi>Zealand</hi> of the ſame Appellation; 'tis about the fourth part of a League in Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:153719:22"/>and extends it ſelf length-ways from North to South, being ſomething more than a League diſtance from the Continent. It has, to the South, a ſteep Rock waſh'd by the Sea, and is wholly encompaſs'd with Rocks, having but one narrow paſſage by which any Veſſels can come to.</p>
            <p>As the <hi>Portugueſe</hi> were the firſt that made any conſiderable Voyages along this Sea, theſe Parts were firſt by them diſcover'd, as well as the remainder of <hi>Affrica</hi> in the Ocean, and <hi>Atlantick</hi> Sea; and falling un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Power of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> they Built a Fort on the weakeſt ſide of the Hill for the Defence of the Iſland, and another ſorry Fort at the Hill foot.</p>
            <p>The Count <hi>D'Eſtrees,</hi> Vice-Admiral of <hi>France,</hi> made himſelf Maſter of this Fort in <hi>November</hi> 1678. it being Surrendred to him by the Governour, without ſo much as putting himſelf in a poſture of Defence; and he not being able to ſpare Force for Manning them, he Demoliſh'd both the one and the other. The Members of the Company, who are in preſent poſſeſſion of this Iſland, have a little repair'd the Lower Fort, having built a ſmall Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zine, and a very indifferent Wall rais'd out of the Ruins of the Old Fort, which are
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:153719:23"/>only capable to prevent the Inſults from their Neighbouring <hi>Negers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Monſieur <hi>Dancourt</hi> immediately em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd himſelf in facilitating the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, and in viſiting the Ware-Houſes along the Coaſts, giving neceſſary Orders to all the Officers that were therein In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted; at length he Eſtabliſh'd a good Correſpondence with the King of the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</hi> and with their Principal Chiefs.</p>
            <p>Upon this Account he travers'd the Country near 24 Leagues a-croſs, from the Mouth of <hi>Senegal</hi> to that of <hi>Gamby,</hi> which are the two main Currants by which the River <hi>Niger</hi> diſimbogues it ſelf into the Sea. I accompanied him in all theſe Journeys along the Coaſts, wherein I made it my buſineſs to inform my ſelf concerning theſe Countries, of the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Manners, and Cuſtoms, of the <hi>Affri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans</hi> of <hi>Cape-Verd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We began our Journey the 6th of <hi>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> 1682. for <hi>Senegal,</hi> whether we could have no paſſage by Sea, by reaſon of a ſtrong Northernly Wind. In the mean time, the State of Affairs requiring the preſence of Monſieur <hi>Dancourt,</hi> upon the Death of the Governor who came thither but ſome days before, he reſolv'd to go
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:153719:23"/>by Land, and to ſend the <hi>Renown,</hi> a Veſſel Commanded by Captain <hi>Oyere,</hi> to carry the Merchandiſes, and to bring back the Goods for which he ſhould make Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changes.</p>
            <p>It were an eaſie matter to come from <hi>Senegal</hi> to <hi>Goree,</hi> but not to go thither. This Veſſel having had a fair Wind, was a Month a making her Paſſage, which would be no more than 40 Leagues in a direct Courſe, but full 500 the way ſhe was oblig'd to take. During this time, we began to imagine that ſhe muſt be loſt, when at length we ſee her come into the Road.</p>
            <p>Our Journey by Land was not ſo long, but much more tireſom, ſince the Road does not furniſh Travellers with the leaſt Neceſſaries. The Guides themſelves are in want; and throughout the whole Village of <hi>Rafis,</hi> which is but 3 Leagues diſtant from hence, we could meet only with one Horſe for Monſieur <hi>Dancourt,</hi> and ſix Aſſes, two of which we Loaded with Proviſions. Mine, I muſt confeſs, had a very brisk Countenance, ſhe winc'd and play'd the Devil for the firſt two Leagues, afterwards ſhe would ſcarce move a foot.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Negers</hi> were weary of beating her,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:153719:24"/>and, indeed, I was oblig'd to diſmount, but ſhe being of no large ſize, I got on and oft without much trouble, having no occaſion for Stirrups. When I lighted upon a piece of bad way, and my Beaſt began to ſtick with me, it was but ſetting my feet to the ground, and ſhe would be perſwaded to move from under me, and leave me fairly to get out my ſelf; finding her ſelf without her Burden, ſhe would kick and run after her Companions with a deal of vigour; which I perceiving, I made bold once more to beſtride her. But, in ſhort, we were deceiv'd in each other; ſhe fairly ſtood ſtill, expecting me to get off as before, and with all the Stripes I was able to give, I could only make her move a Foot-pace, as gravely as the <hi>Portugueſe</hi> himſelf to whom ſhe belong'd. Her Back was ſo ſharp, that ſhe inflicted the ſame pain as the Wooden-Horſe. In ſhort, without any fault of my own, was I thus rack'd during the whole ſix days of our Journey.</p>
            <p>Though it were in the Month of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember,</hi> yet the heat was inſufferable; which added much to my grievances, we continuing our march from Sun ſet to Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing, making only a ſmall Halt at Noon,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:153719:24"/>where, under the ſhade of Trees, we took ſome refreſhment out of the Proviſions we brought along with us. At Night we Lodg'd in a ſmall Village, but we found neither Victuals for our ſelves, nor Mill for our Carriers, which is the ordinary Food of the <hi>Negers,</hi> who often, for want of Corn, live entirely upon Roots.</p>
            <p>Our Landlords entertain'd us after the beſt manner they were able, but their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream Poverty made even that moſt inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable. Their Houſes are made of Straw, even that which belongs to the King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. There are ſome places, where they are made more Commodious than in others. Theſe worthy Structures are about four paces Diameter; their Covering is round, in the ſhape of a Dome; the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per part whereof is Straw, and the under Palm Leaves, the whole very prettily work'd: The Dome is ſupported with five or ſix forked Staves: The Wall is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with Straw or Palm-Leaves curiouſly interwoven.</p>
            <p>They have neither Doors nor Windows to their Houſes, ſave only a Hole much reſembling the Mouth of an Oven; ſo that whoever goes in or out, muſt do it upon all four. Though the Heat muſt
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:153719:25"/>needs be exceſſive in ſuch a ſtreightned place, yet they cannot content themſelves without a fire, which muſt of neceſſity make an intolerable Smoak, which to them is very agreeable, they taking a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar delight in Smoak. The Floor of the Houſe is Sand, having Trenches digg'd in them half Leg deep.</p>
            <p>Some of their Houſes have their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance ſo very ſmall, that I admir'd how they could poſſibly creep in and out. And I remember a Gentleman, of ſomething a larger ſize than my ſelf, having lain in one of theſe lovely Palaces, endeavouring to creep out like a Serpent, having half out he very fairly ſtuck by the middle. In vain I endeavour'd to help him, and not daring to cut the Wall, I was oblig'd to call help to drag the Spark out.</p>
            <p>Their Beds are ſtill more incommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious than their Houſes; they are made with a parcel of Sticks as thick as a Man's Wriſt, plac'd two Fingers breadth aſunder in the Nature of a Hurdle; the great knotty Sticks thus Platted, ſeem made on purpoſe to break a Man's Back. Their Beds, as well as their Houſes, are ſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with forked Sticks: They lye down upon them without any more to do,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:153719:25"/>though thoſe of the better ſort of Quality have a Mat, which ſerves inſtead of a Quilt.</p>
            <p>By this that I have already ſaid, 'tis eaſie to conclude, that though their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try can't afford its Inhabitants any great Felicities, by reaſon of its Sterility, yet their Lazineſs does much contribute to their Miſeries.</p>
            <p>But to return to our Journey, which this digreſſion has interrupted: After ſix days Travelling, we were got to a Village call'd <hi>Bieure,</hi> at the Mouth of the River <hi>Senegal.</hi> We found it to be the Cuſtom of the Country, for their Women only to meddle in the buſineſs of Traffick, their Men not concerning themſelves at all; ſo that out of pretext of bringing down their Merchandiſe, the Women come to divert themſelves amongſt our Seamen, who often are very ready to oblige them.</p>
            <p>We left our Equipage here, and Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Dancourt</hi> ſent to the Reſidence, that they might ſend him a Bark to carry us the remaining 5 Leagues, to the Iſland <hi>St. Louis,</hi> which is made by <hi>Senegal;</hi> where we happily arriv'd on the 13th of <hi>December,</hi> two hours after Midnight.</p>
            <p>This Iſland is ſituated in the middle of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:153719:26"/>the River, 5 Leagues above its Mouth, and is about a League in Circumference: The Company have there a Store-Houſe, a Commandant and Commiſſioners; 'tis thither where the <hi>Negers</hi> bring their Skins, Ivory, Slaves, and ſometimes Amber-Gris; for our Gum-Arabick, it comes from the <hi>Moors,</hi> as I have already men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd.</p>
            <p>We give in Exchange, to theſe <hi>Negers,</hi> Linnen, Cotton, Copper, Tin, <hi>Aqua. Vitae,</hi> and ſome Glaſs-baubles. The Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages that accrues by this ſort of Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick, is 8 Hundred for the Hundred: The Skins, the Ivory, and the Gum, are brought into <hi>France;</hi> for the Slaves, they are ſent to the <hi>French</hi> Plantations in <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica,</hi> to be employ'd in the Sugar Works.</p>
            <p>Thoſe of the better ſort are purchas'd ſop eight <hi>Francs</hi> each, and are re-ſold for above a Hundred Crowns. You'll ofte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> have a good ſubſtantial Slave for four o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> five Quarts of <hi>Aqua-Vitae.</hi> Thus their Prie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> is ſmall, but the Charges of Tranſportin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> amounts to ſomething conſiderable.</p>
            <p>The River of <hi>Senegal</hi> is a Branch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Niger,</hi> ſeparating it ſelf about 600 League<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> above its Entrance: This River diffuſes i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſelf in the Kingdom of <hi>Cantorſi,</hi> and from
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:153719:26"/>thence ſpreads into ſeveral Branches; the principal of which are <hi>Gamby</hi> and <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>organde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Senegal</hi> ſepanates the <hi>Azonghes, Moors</hi> or <hi>Tawnies,</hi> from the real <hi>Blacks;</hi> ſo that on one ſide of the River are the <hi>Moors</hi> of a Tawny Complexion, and the other is Inhabited by People that are perfectly Black. The former are Wanderers, ſtill Encamping, and making no longer ſtay in a place than they are furniſh'd with good Paſturage; whereas the others, to wit, the <hi>Negers,</hi> are Sedentry, and aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate themſelves in Villages.</p>
            <p>Thoſe have no. Superiors but what they voluntarily chooſe, but theſe are ſubjected to Kings, who Deſpotically Tyrannize over them, and render them meer Slaves and Vaſſals. The <hi>Moors</hi> are ſmall, Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and of an uncouth Mien, but have a Genius that's free and refin'd. On the contrary, the <hi>Negers</hi> are large, fat, and well proportion'd, but very Silly, and of ſhallow Conceptions. The Country In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited by the <hi>Moors</hi> is a Barren Sand, deſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ce of Greens; and that of the <hi>Nigers</hi> fertile in Paſturage, Mill, and ever Greens, though they produce no Fruit for Suſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:153719:27"/>
            <p>It is from theſe <hi>Moors</hi> that we have our Gum-Arabick; they gather it in the Deſarts of the interior <hi>Lybia.</hi> It ſticks to the Trees that diſcharge it, as that of Cherry and Plum-Trees in <hi>France:</hi> They expoſe it to Sale a Month or ſix Weeks before the Inundation of <hi>Niger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We give them in Exchange blue Cloth, blue Linnen, and ſome ſmall quantities of Iron; they bring it 5 or 600 Leagues by Land; ſome have half a Quintal, ſome more, and others leſs. They Ride wholly Naked upon their Camels, Horſes, or Beeves, which they make uſe of for car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying, their Merchandiſes. Thoſe of the greateſt Rank amongſt them, have a kind of Mantle made of Furr'd Skins, which very much reſemble the Hoods of our Chanters; others have only a ſorry piece of Leather to cover their Nudities. They make uſe of little other Nouriſhment but Milk, with ſome Gum diſſolv'd therein.</p>
            <p>They are accuſtom'd to feed in Gangs when they come down to Traffick; and ſometimes they buy a Beef expreſly to devour him, but muſt themſelves out his Throat, otherwiſe they will not eat of him; and there are thoſe amongſt, who are ſet a part for that piece of Service
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:153719:27"/>Though they have good ſtore of Cattle, yet they rarely eat any, ſave only when they have ſome one that is ready to expire, either by ſome Diſtemper, or by Age.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that Negotiate with them have an intolerable deal of trouble, ſince they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways meet with either Cheating or Inſult from their hands; but ſince the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce is drove on the Bank of the River, they cannot ſo eaſily Cheat, for the Goods are immediately put on Board as they are Meaſur'd from them. This Commerce is perform'd in the Months of <hi>May</hi> and <hi>June,</hi> 30 Leagues above our Reſidence.</p>
            <p>When all is finiſh'd, they begin to Rattle you with a thouſand opprobrious Reproaches; and if they can Trepan any <hi>French,</hi> or other White Man, they certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kill him in Revenge of ſome Quarrel, though of 20 Years ſtanding. No longer than two Months ſince, they had taken a Seaman that knew the Language, who was ſent by a Captain of the Company to <hi>Arguin,</hi> and they demanded no leſs than 50 Slaves in Exchange of him.</p>
            <p>Never was Nation more Roguiſh and Perfidious: They are very Cunning; and can make uſe of Fire Arms, but dare not ſtand a Shot; ſo that three White Men
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:153719:28"/>did once prevent more than four hundred from ſeizing of a Bark, with which theſe Infidels came to Traffick; the Musket-ſhot which they were ply'd withal, did utterly Diſarm them of their Courage, and baulk their Treachery.</p>
            <p>It was known afterwards, that the moſt part of them were <hi>Moors</hi> from the Skirts of <hi>Mount-Atlas,</hi> who came to Depoſe <hi>Cheiratick,</hi> one of the moſt puiſſant <hi>Negers</hi> Princes of that Country; of whom I ſhall ſpeak more hereafter. I had forgot to mention that they retire into the Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands, as ſoon as the <hi>Niger</hi> begins to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow.</p>
            <p>The Kingdom of <hi>Senegal</hi> is the firſt Land belonging to the <hi>Negers:</hi> It has been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly very conſiderable, at preſent it is of ſmall Note; though they have a very brave King, yet, for want of Force, this Prince is become Tributary to another.</p>
            <p>His Dominion extends it ſelf along the River for the ſpace of 40 Leagues, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reckoning ſome petty Signiories about its Mouth, and about 10 or 12 Leagues into Land; all which are his Tributaries.</p>
            <p>This King is call'd <hi>Brac,</hi> which is an Appellation of Dignity; however Abſolute he is, yet is he ſo Poor and Miſerable, bib
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:153719:28"/>that often he has not Mill for his own Support. He is ſo great a Lover of Horſes, that for the generality he contents him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with a Pipe of Tobacco, and a ſmall quantity of <hi>Aqua-Vitae,</hi> and ſpares his Mill to give his Horſes. Sometimes he makes Incurſions upon the moſt unprovided of his Neighbours, without the leaſt pretext, and ſo drives off their Cattel, in which their Riches conſiſt; nay, often makes a parcel of Slaves, whom he ſells for <hi>Aqua-Vitae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When his Stock of Strong-Water di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhes, he Looks up the remaining quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity in a ſmall Cheſt, and gives the Key to one of his Favourites, whom he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patches, perhaps, 30 Leagues from thence, to tell ſome fooliſh Story to his Wein<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n. This he does, that he may not have pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to Drink during his abſence with the Key, by which means his ſmall Store is preſerv'd.</p>
            <p>If he has no opportunity of exerciſing his Tyranny upon his Neighbours, he does not fall of giving his own Subjec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> a taſte of it, by over running his own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, ſtaying two days in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> one, Village, three in another, where he exacts an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment for himſelf and all his Court;
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:153719:29"/>which is compos'd of 200 of thoſe that are moſt exquiſite in Roguery, Raſcals that have refin'd themſelves by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce with the Whites, of whom they are ſure to retain their worſt qualities. After they have ruin'd the Town, they take oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to carry off ſome Slaves, upon the leaſt pretence of injury imag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nable.</p>
            <p>And if the Prince be Perfidious, his Subjects don't come an Inch behind him, for they will lay hold on all opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to ſell each other, without the leaſt regard either to the degrees of Sanguini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; ſo that a Father will ſell his Sons, and a Son his Parents, as it beſt happens. They will pretend to employ thoſe whom they have a mind to ſell, in helping them with their Goods to our Reſidence, and when they have them there, they deliver them to whoever will purchaſe them, if they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not the Language.</p>
            <p>I will inſert here an Adventure that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd ſome time ſince, which will verify what I have been ſaying. One of theſe Wretches had form'd a deſign of ſelling his Son, he perceiving it diſſembled the thing, and underſtanding the <hi>French</hi> Tongue, whilſt his Father was gone ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where aſide he went to our Store-Houſe,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:153719:29"/>and told, That he had a Jolly Slave to diſpoſe of; and, in ſhort, the Price was agreed on, and the bargain concluded, he ſold and deliver'd him. This Slave was his own Father, who ſeeing them go to put Irons on his Feet, he began to be in a paſſion, and cry'd out, He was his Father; he deny'd it, and the Bargain ſtood good.</p>
            <p>This Crime did not go long unpuniſh'd, for the Son going home again with his Merchandiſe, met with a powerful Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niour, who fairly ſtripp'd him of what he had, made him a Slave, and ſold him at our Reſidence.</p>
            <p>After the Kingdom of <hi>Brac,</hi> you meet with that of <hi>Cheyratick;</hi> which is as much as to ſay, the moſt potent of the Empire. Of this latter depends more than ten little Kings, and other mean Soveraigns: His Empire extends it ſelf upon two branches of the River <hi>Senegal,</hi> and contains full 300 Leagues of Land. Theſe Countries pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce Dates, Mill, and plentiful Paſtures for feeding great ſtore of Cattel. Theſe People are call'd <hi>Foules;</hi> they are not quite black, neither ſo white as the <hi>Moors,</hi> but are betwixt both.</p>
            <p>They are far more Civiliz'd than the reſt of the <hi>Negers,</hi> and entertain Strangers
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:153719:30"/>very civilly. It has very often happen'd, when any of our Seamen have been ill treated by their Captains, they have taken Refuge at the Court of <hi>Cheyratick,</hi> where they have been kindly receiv'd, admitted to his Table, and have partaken of all the ſatisfaction and diverſions that the place was capable of affording.</p>
            <p>He, for the moſt part, feeds upon Mill, Beef, and Dates, and never Drinks ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Wine or <hi>Aqua-Vitae,</hi> obſerving the Precepts of <hi>Mahomet</hi> more Religiouſly than the other <hi>Negers;</hi> he can take the Field with 50000 men, but for want of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions he cannot long ſubſiſt them.</p>
            <p>Aſcending from the Eſtates of <hi>Cheyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick,</hi> you meet with the Countries of <hi>Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gots</hi> and <hi>Engusland,</hi> 300 Leagues from our Reſidence; we alſo manage a Traffick with them. They differ not in the leaſt from the <hi>Foules.</hi> Since it is impoſſible to get any higher, my knowledge of thoſe Countries reaches no farther; nor do I know a tittle of any thing beyond.</p>
            <p>After the River <hi>Senegal</hi> has winded it ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lf about <hi>Cantercy,</hi> and ſeveral other large Iſlands, it empties it ſelf into the Sea, by two ſeveral Paſſages, in 15 Degrees 32 Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes Northern Latitude. Betwixt the Sea
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:153719:30"/>and this River there lies a Flat, or Bed of Sand, of about a Cannon-ſhot over; this reſiſtance forces it to continue its Courſe for 6 Leagues before it can diſcharge it ſelf into the Sea, though their ſurface lies of an equal level, but when it has forc'd it ſelf two ſeveral Paſſages, it diſembogues it ſelf by two Mouths into the Sea, of about two Leagues diſtant from each other, between which is found an Iſland.</p>
            <p>In each of theſe Chanels there ariſes ſeveral Sand-Banks, which the River waſhes down with it, and are caſt up back again by the Sea, and are left in dangerous ridges very incommodious for the Shipping for want of open Chanels; the continual agitation of the Sea, meeting a reſiſtance by the Banks, render the Waves of a terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble largeneſs, whoſe force do often ſplit the Veſſels againſt the ſhore; and then there is no manner of help for the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, for ſhould they endeavour to ſave themſelves by Swimming, they would be immediately devour'd by the <hi>Requiems.</hi> Theſe Paſſages are only dangerous at Low-Water, and not at the over-flowing of the <hi>Niger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is ſingular in theſe Inundations, is that they almoſt, every time the Waters
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:153719:31"/>riſe, force themſelves new Paſſages through the Sands to get into the Sea. About 20 Years paſt, it made its entrance right againſt the Iſland which is Inhabited by the <hi>French,</hi> which oblig'd them to remove a little higher; which Paſſage is now clos'd, and others made a-new, which are ſtill ſo interchangeably fill'd, that there, however, remains but two at one time.</p>
            <p>Several Nations of <hi>Europe</hi> have Traffick'd formerly in this River, at preſent they are only <hi>French</hi> that uſe that Trade.</p>
            <p>Perhaps, having often mention'd the Inundation of <hi>Niger,</hi> it may be requir'd that I ſhould give an Account how, and at what time it increaſes, without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to give any Phyſical Reaſons for its ſo doing; if by the Relation of the circumſtances ſuch a knowledge may be forwarded, I will do my beſt to recount the Particulars, ſuch as I found them.</p>
            <p>The Heats are very exceſſive under the Torrid Zone for want of Rains, which are here very rare, and never out of the Months of <hi>July, Auguſt,</hi> and <hi>September.</hi> On the South-ſide of the Equinoctial the Rains begin earlier, and eſpecially falls in abundance at this Seaſon; they are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company'd with furious Winds, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:153719:31"/>by ſo great a Calm, and ſuch ſoul tring Heats, that 'tis very troubleſome to breath. After the interval of two or three hours the Tempeſt recommences, and holds thus ſucceſſively during the three Months; this occaſions violent Diſtempers, Fevers, <hi>Cholera-Morbus,</hi> Ulcers upon the Legs, frequent Convulſions, follow'd by Death or the Palſie.</p>
            <p>The Reaſons of the Inundation of the <hi>Nile</hi> are ſufficiently known, nor have I any occaſion to repeat them; this of the <hi>Niger</hi> is, no doubt, produc'd by the ſame Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipals. I believe that the true cauſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from the Sun's repaſſing the Line of <hi>Cancer,</hi> which in <hi>France</hi> makes our Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Solſtice; and here the Winter draws together a great Maſs of Vapours, which are afterwards diſcuſs'd into great and continued Rains, which, conſequently, cauſe the overflowing.</p>
            <p>Theſe Rains begin in <hi>Aethiopia</hi> in <hi>April,</hi> and continue <hi>May</hi> and <hi>June,</hi> but here they begin the 15th of <hi>July;</hi> they hold en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing for the ſpace of 40 days, and are as long in their decreaſe. This Inunda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which enriches the Soil, is not gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, but only on the Country that borders upon the River. When you are once up,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:153719:32"/>the Courſe of the River is no longer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, ſince its Chanel has not depth enough to contain theſe Waters, nor pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to convey them ſtreight into the Sea; ſo that they fill up all the Vallies, and lay the whole Country in a level.</p>
            <p>It's dangerous Sailing during this Flood, eſpecially on the River <hi>Senegal,</hi> when the Chanel cannot be known; for upon the decreaſe of the Water the Bark may be left either upon ſome eminence, or in ſome hollow, of which it would be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to get her clear.</p>
            <p>It is about 15 Years ago ſince an Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent happen'd, which will confirm what I. have ſaid. The Gentlemen of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany having a mind to take the benefit of the Flood, ſent ſome Barks to diſcover the Inhabitants about the place, and where the Branches of the <hi>Niger</hi> ſeparate; they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to Sail from the River of <hi>Senegal</hi> to that of <hi>Gamby,</hi> of whoſe entrance the <hi>Engliſh</hi> are Maſters; and by a Fort which they there maintain, they hinder any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce by others into that River. And ſince our People could no how make any Diſcoveries that way, but at the time of the high Waters, by whoſe aſſiſtance they might Sail over Rocks, which at other
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:153719:32"/>times ſtood on dry ground. They ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 30 Men in theſe Barks, who went up nea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 300 Leagues from our Reſidence, but they underwent ſuch Fatigues, that but five o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them return'd. Having one time loſt the Chanel, their Bark, amongſt other Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes ſtuck faſt amongſt the Trees; by good Luck they were not far off the Chanel, ſo that by force and main ſtrength they got her once more afloat.</p>
            <p>When Monſieur <hi>Dancourt</hi> had diſpatch'd his buſineſs in theſe Quarters, in what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to the advantage of the Company, finding the <hi>Barbarre,</hi> or the Mouth of the River, in good condition to be paſs'd, there being a gentle Eaſterly Wind, he accompliſh'd it in a Bark appointed for that purpoſe; ſhe carry'd us Aboard the Ship call'd the <hi>Ronown,</hi> who waited for us in the Road, on which we Embark'd to ſave a troubleſome Journey by Land.</p>
            <p>We weigh'd Anchor the 10th of <hi>Janua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> 1683, and Sail'd for <hi>Goree;</hi> we Coaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed along the ſhore, which being adorn'd with Trees of a continual Green, afforded us a moſt engaging Proſpect.</p>
            <p>When he had viſited all the Coaſts, and given his neceſſary Orders, we return'd the lame way, which took us up eight
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:153719:33"/>hole days. I have here ſet down what Remarks I was capable of making during my ſmall continuance there.</p>
            <p>The People that Inhabit the Coaſts from the Mouth of <hi>Senegal</hi> to that of <hi>Gamby,</hi> are divided into three ſorts, The <hi>Geloffes,</hi> the <hi>Sereres,</hi> and the <hi>Barbecins;</hi> they are go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd by ſeveral little Kinglings, each Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute in his own Territories: He of largeſt Bounds is King <hi>Amel,</hi> Sovereign of the <hi>Geloffes.</hi> The Name <hi>Amel</hi> is not pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to this Prince, but it is a Name of Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. Since all their Governments do very much reſembe each other, as well in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the People as the Country, I ſhall content my ſelf with this Example, to make you ſenſible of the others.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Geloffes</hi> Inhabit beyond the Mouth of <hi>Senegal</hi> as you go South, till you come within 6 or 7 Leagues of <hi>Cape-Verd,</hi> which contains, from North to South, 40 Leagues of the Maritime Coaſts, and from Eaſt to Weſt 100 by Land.</p>
            <p>The Country of the <hi>Sereres,</hi> have for their King him whom we call <hi>Portugady,</hi> by reaſon of a Town that belongs to him, and bears this Name; <hi>Jain</hi> is his Name of Dignity. It contains 10 or 12 Leagues along the Coaſt, and extends it ſelf almoſt an hundred by Land.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:153719:33"/>
            <p>The Kingdom of <hi>Barbecins,</hi> otherwiſe <hi>Jouall,</hi> (for the ſame reaſon as I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd of <hi>Sereres</hi>) is govern'd by King whoſe Name I cannot call to mind; he has no larger Territories than the former, with whom he often wages War.</p>
            <p>Beſides theſe three People, there are a ſort of <hi>Portugueſe;</hi> they are ſo call'd, ſince they deſcended from them who firſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited theſe Coaſts after their firſt Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very. The <hi>Negreſſes,</hi> whom they eſpous'd, brought forth theſe kind of Mule men, from whom there comes a Race ſtill more ſwarthy. They may alſo be Fugitives from <hi>Cape-Verd,</hi> or from <hi>Cacheau,</hi> another Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony of that Nation, upon one of the Branches of the River <hi>Gamby,</hi> diſtant three days Journey. As they have follow'd the Religion of their Ancient Maſters, they are partly Jews, partly Catholicks; they carry a great pair of Beads about their Necks; there are none of any greater Rank than others; they are great Cheats, and very Malicious, having all the Vices of the <hi>Portugueſe,</hi> and not one of their good Qualities.</p>
            <p>All theſe parts in general are Sandy and Barren; the Heat is more violent in the Month of <hi>January,</hi> than it is in <hi>July</hi> or
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:153719:34"/>
               <hi>Auguſt</hi> in <hi>France.</hi> It Rains in the ſame manner, as I have already ſaid, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſpoke of <hi>Senegal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Country is well Peopled, and is very Woody. They begin at the end of <hi>June</hi> to Cultivate their Land, and Sow their Seed; ſome ſmall while after the Rains have ceas'd. Their Harveſt falls our in <hi>September;</hi> ſo that in three Months time they prepare their Land Sow and Gather in. This makes the Richneſs of the Soil apparent, which, notwithſtanding its Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rility, and their Natural Lazineſs, produces them great ſtore of Grain; I mean their Mill.</p>
            <p>Their way of labouring their Earth is odd and pleaſant: They get four or five together in the Field, which they call <hi>Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan;</hi> or <hi>Courgar,</hi> and ſo with a little round Iron Shovel, ſomething larger than ones Hand, ſet in a Stale of Wood, they break up the Earth, which they fling be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, not entring the Swerd of the Ground above three or four ſingers breadth, each having a Pipe conſtantly in his Mouth. If they Work one hour, they'l beſure to Chat two for it. When the Ground is ſo order'd, they Sow it as they Sow Peaſe in <hi>France,</hi> and never take care to lay
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:153719:34"/>by any Store. They are for the moſt part ſo Lazy, that they don't gather half enough to ſerve them, living in the mean time upon a black Root, which is dry'd till it afford no manner of ſavour; and upon another call'd <hi>Gernotte,</hi> whoſe taſte is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing like that of a Wall-nut. If by chance their Harveſt miſs, and they are left deſtitute of a Crop, they even dye of Hunger.</p>
            <p>It is not five Years ſince the like mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune happen'd to them, being ſeduc'd by the promiſes of a <hi>Marabon,</hi> which is the name of their Prieſts: He was of the <hi>Azoaghes,</hi> or <hi>Arabs,</hi> of which I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſpoken. Under pretence of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, he poſſeſs'd himſelf of all the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try betwixt <hi>Cheyratick</hi> to <hi>Sereres,</hi> telling them, That he was inſpir'd by Heaven to revenge the Tyranny of their Kings. He promis'd Miraculous Forces to prove his Vocation; and, above all, to make their Land bring forth a plentiful and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary Harveſt, without giving them any trouble of beſtowing their Labour.</p>
            <p>This Promiſe ſuiting well with their idle temper, tickled their Imaginations at a ſtrange rate; ſo that almoſt all of them, eſpecially thoſe of the Kingdom of <hi>Damel,</hi>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:153719:35"/>eſpous'd the Cauſe of this Impoſtor. Their King was Depos'd, and all their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours Pillag'd in this Revolt; they liv'd in daily expectation of this Miracle, and waited two Years looking for their Mill, but to no purpoſe. At length they began to Eat one another for want of Suſtenance, and afterwards were oblig'd to ſurrender themſelves Slaves. Proceſs of time con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd them of their folly and madneſs; ſo they drove away their Tyrant, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor'd <hi>Damel</hi> to his Eſtate. At preſent they will allow no more <hi>Marabous</hi> in their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, but make Slaves of all they can lay their hands on.</p>
            <p>Beſides their Mill, they have black and white Beans, very like our <hi>French</hi> Beans, and Melons full of an inſipid Juice. Of this ſort of Grain, they make that which they call <hi>Couſcouſe</hi> in <hi>Arabs</hi> and <hi>Laguere</hi> in their Language, which is their ordinary ſort of Food. The Fruit which we call <hi>Bananes,</hi> and in the <hi>Canaries Adam</hi>'s Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, are very plentiful amongſt them. They feed Cattle and Goats; and thoſe amongſt them which have the largeſt Stock, are of the greateſt Repute. Their Beefs are no larger than a Calf of eight or nine Months old in <hi>France,</hi> which I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:153719:35"/>is occaſion'd by their great Droughts; for all along the Banks of the River <hi>Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal,</hi> which affords good Paſturage, they are as large as in <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are great ſtore of Palm-Trees, of which I obſerv'd three ſeveral ſorts: The one reſembles the Date-Tree, the other like them we have in <hi>France;</hi> the third is a ſort of <hi>Latanier.</hi> As for that which bears the <hi>Coco,</hi> there is none of that kind here.</p>
            <p>By Inciſions which the <hi>Negers</hi> make in theſe Palm-Trees, a Liquor is Diſtill'd of a Pearl colour, which they call Palm-Wine, 'tis ſweet and palatable to be made uſe of the firſt day, it entoxicates, and loſes its guſt, every day growing ſowrer than other; the older it is, the more it affects the Head. Each Tree may produce three Pints of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor; it is generally made uſe of for the Regaling of Strangers, nor is it ever want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing amongſt the Perſons of Condition. This ſame Tree produces a ſort of ſmall <hi>Coco's,</hi> from which they draw the <hi>Punick</hi> Oil; which ſmells like Violets, is of a Saffron colour, and taſtes like Olives; it makes part of the Compoſition of the <hi>Muſſelin</hi>-Oil of <hi>Nicolas Alexandrin.</hi> Some Cuſtoms from theſe Trees are due to <hi>Alzair,</hi> or the Lord of the Village.</p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:153719:36"/>
            <p>As the Palm-Trees are high and without Branches, and that the Inciſion muſt be made in two or three places below the Tuft of Boughs, which is the Beauty of this Tree, they climb up after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: They have a round Hoop made of Bark, which they can tye and untye as they pleaſe, by which they mount; they ſeem as if they ſat within it, and puſh their Feet againſt the Tree, ſuſtain'd by the Rind which goes about their Thighs, and holds them as firm as though they ſat upon the Ground. Thus they Inch up till they get to the top, where they make their Inciſions, and fix too their <hi>Calabaſſes</hi> to catch the diſtilling Liquor. You can't look upon them ſo high, upheld by ſo ſmall a matter, without being ſenſible of ſome dread and terror.</p>
            <p>All along the Coaſts they have an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite number of Animals, of which I ſhan't pretend to give a particular Deſcription, ſince I am not well-skill'd in the Science of the Naturaliſts; I ſhall only mention them that I know, of which many may be ſeen in <hi>Europe,</hi> by the Care and Curioſity of ſeveral Princes that have occaſion'd their Tranſporting: But ſeeing them there in their Natural fierceneſs, before they are
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:153719:36"/>any ways tam'd, what I have to ſay con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them may, perhaps, give you ſome more particular Ideas.</p>
            <p>The places where, for the moſt part, theſe wild Creatures are ſeen, are Ponds and Ditches which the Rain has fill'd up; Evenings and Mornings they come thither by Droves, as well as others that be leſs Savage: There are then to be ſeen <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phants, Lions, Tygers, Leopards, Ounces, Wolves, Tyger-Cats,</hi> ſuch as produce <hi>Civet, Foxes, Wild Goats,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>What they obſerve of an <hi>Elephant,</hi> is, That ſhe is never to be attack'd where there is room enough for her quick and free turning; for when ſhe is at liberty, ſhe will certainly overturn the Men with her Trunk, and trample them to Death. I do not know the time when the Female brings forth her Young, what I know, is, That ſhe often has three at a time, and feeds them with Herbs and Leaves, which ſhe puts in their Mouths with her Trunk. They often come by Night into the Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, not at all concerning themſelves tho' they be frequented places; and inſtead of turning out of the way, when they meet with any of the <hi>Negers</hi> Houſes, they keep ſtreight forwards, and overturn them in
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:153719:37"/>their Walk as tho' they were but Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhells.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Lyon</hi> is very curious and cunning in ſeizing his Prey, not leaping directly upon it, but taking a compaſs, ramping upon the Ground, and when he finds him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf within compaſs, he darts forth and flings himſelf upon it. They are eaſily tam'd when Young, we having had of them as gentle and as fawning as a Dog.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Tyger</hi> is more fierce than the <hi>Lyon,</hi> his length and heighth is near the ſame with a Greyhounds, and will indifferently fall upon either Man or Beaſt. The <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> kill many of them with their <hi>Zagayes,</hi> and their Arrows, that they may get their Skins; whatever Wound they have receiv'd, yet they keep upon the Defence during they have any life left, and ſcarce ever fail of killing ſome before they fall.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Leopard</hi> is cruel and nimble; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, they do not care for attacking Men, unleſs they meet them in a place ſo nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row that they cannot be avoided; but then he flings himſelf upon them, tearing their Faces with their Claws, pulling off as much fleſh as they can graſp, and thus killing them. They are Mortal Enemies to the Dogs, and devour them where-ever they meet them.</p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:153719:37"/>
            <p>They ſay the <hi>Ounce</hi> is ſtill more fierce than a <hi>Tyger,</hi> of which I believe they are a Species, or, at leaſt, what we call <hi>Panthers;</hi> their Skin is more beautiful than the <hi>Tygers,</hi> though they be ſpotted alike.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Tyger-Cat</hi> is alſo ſo call'd, by reaſon of his black and white ſpots; they are ſhap'd like our Cats, but four times as large; naturally voracious, and eats Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kies, Rats, and other ſort of Animals.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Wolfe</hi> differs in no reſpect from ours, but that they are ſomething larger, and more cruel.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Cat,</hi> which produces the Civet, has the Head and Muzzel of a Fox; it is large and ſpotted like the other, and very wild. One may get Civet from them every two days; which is a ſort of <hi>Muſcoſite,</hi> or thick Sweat, which is under their Breech, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a concavity which contains their Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles.</p>
            <p>I never ſaw any <hi>Rhinoceros,</hi> tho' there be ſome here. There are ſeveral ſort of <hi>Apes</hi> and <hi>Monkies,</hi> as the <hi>Guenons</hi> with long Tails, and <hi>Magots</hi> which have none at all; I ſaw none of theſe latter. For the former there are ſtore every where, of which there are three kinds; two of which are of a ſmall Compoſure, and do but
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:153719:38"/>little miſchef. Of theſe leſſer ſort, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> call ſome of them the <hi>Bewailers,</hi> by reaſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of a Cry like unto ſmall Children.</p>
            <p>Of the other ſort, there are ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> large as the <hi>Magots;</hi> they have not onl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Hands and Feet, but have ſomething ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> near Mankind in their Geſture. The <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> are fully convinc'd that theſe Ape<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> can ſpeak if they pleaſe, but that they do not leſt they ſhould be oblig'd to Work Though we know that theſe Creatures are good for nothing but to bite and tear, y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> they often meet with a great deal of kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs at our hands. It is, I believe, on th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> account that the <hi>Negers</hi> of <hi>Senegal</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> bring Rats in Cages, as though we wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fond of all ſorts of Beaſts; and they'l te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> you, that thoſe are more Brave and C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious than the Monkies, and that therefo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> we ought to love them more.</p>
            <p>It is not to be imagin'd what Havo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> theſe Creatures make, when the Mill an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Corn is ripe, on which they fee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> They will get 40 or 50 of them together and ſo go to <hi>Cougan;</hi> one of them is plac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Sentinel upon ſome high Tree near th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Field, whil'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r the reſt are buſie at the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Harveſt. Whenever he perceives any bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy a coming, he will Cry like a Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing;
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:153719:38"/>the others of the Gang taking hint at the Signal, get off with their Booty with all the ſpeed imaginable, leaping from Tree to Tree with a prodigious agility. And the Females, who carry their Young along with them, will, notwithſtanding, leap the Trees to a Miracle, as tho' they were not at all incumbred.</p>
            <p>They eat here great ſtore of Veniſon. Wild Boars are very plentiful, but have not the ſame reliſh as ours, and their fleſh is as white as that of a young Pig. Wild Goats, Kids and Hares, are in great ſtore.</p>
            <p>I did not ſee any of their <hi>Stags,</hi> which are headed as well as in <hi>France,</hi> only their Horns are like thoſe of the <hi>Capricorns</hi> in the Mountains of <hi>Switzerland,</hi> ſaving that they are ſtreight.</p>
            <p>There is to be ſeen here ſeveral Species of Birds unknown in <hi>Europe,</hi> abundance of which live altogether upon Fiſh; particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, they have one they call the <hi>Great Goſier,</hi> they are twice as big as a Swan, having a Beak a full Cubit in length, and a Craw of Skin under their Throat in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſhion of a bag, they ſwallow Fiſh entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y whole, tho' as large as a good middling Carp. <hi>Cormorants</hi> and <hi>Vultures</hi> are the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ame as in <hi>Europe:</hi> Of theſe latter ſort
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:153719:39"/>there are ſome as large as Eagles, which will devour ſmall Children whenever they can catch them a ſtragling.</p>
            <p>I ſaw ſome Birds of ſo changeable and ſo curious a Plumage, that it's impoſſible for me to give you a juſt Deſcription: Their <hi>Nightingals</hi> do not warble ſo ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as in <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have already mention'd the <hi>Oſtridges,</hi> of which ſome are of an exceſſive large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; thoſe of them that are Flyers are delicious Food, and their ſeveral parts have a diſtinct reliſh; they are as large as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Swan, and their Plumes are grey and black. The <hi>Wild Geeſe</hi> are very good and pleaſant Food: Their <hi>Teal,</hi> above all the other Fowl, have a moſt incomparable reliſh; and thoſe of them that are grey upon the River <hi>Senegal,</hi> do much ſurpa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the reſt in goodneſs.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Partridges</hi> there do Pearch upon Trees like other Birds; as alſo do their <hi>Hens,</hi> which the <hi>Portugueſe</hi> call <hi>Pintade<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Theſe Hens are ſpeckled grey, and black having a ſmall red Wattel on each ſid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their Ears; they are of a larger ſize that ours, and I believe them to be a kind <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Partridges.</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:153719:39"/>
            <p>The <hi>Parrots</hi> there are of two kinds, the one are ſmall, and wholly Green; the other are larger, with grey Heads, their Bellies yellow, their Wings green, and their Backs a mixture of grey and yellow. Theſe never talk, but the ſmall ones have a clear and ſweet Voice, and will learn whatever is taught them.</p>
            <p>Of all thoſe different Birds, I know none that are ſo curiouſly Induſtrious, as a certain ſmall Bird that makes its Neſt upon the Palm-Trees, after a moſt curious way of Architecture, and by a wonderful In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct, ſecures it from the Serpents that often creep up the Trees. They build them on the extream Point of the ſmalleſt Branches, to which they faſten a Ruſh or S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>raw, the ſtrongeſt that they are able to carry, of about a Foot and a half in length; and to the end which hangs down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in the Air, do they ſtrangely affix their Neſts, leaving a ſmall hole for their entrance on one ſide near the top. This reſembles a Ball hung up by a Thread and ſince the Branch to which it is affix'd is too ſmall to bear any offenſive Creature, they there produce their Young in ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:153719:40"/>
            <p>The Sea is extraordinary full of Fiſh along the Coaſts, where all ſorts may be met withal: Thoſe of Prey have large and long Teeth, of a double or triple range. Thoſe that are commonly Eat there, are <hi>Parques, Guiltheads, Vieills, Tun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nys, Mullets, Rucaes</hi> of the ſhape of a Salmon, <hi>Negres, Soles, Smelts,</hi> and in abundance of <hi>Sprats;</hi> by which the Sea is ſometimes cover'd.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Requiem</hi> is a Sea-Monſter, of the ſhape of a Sea-Dog, but as long as three of them; from four to eight Foot in length. She brings forth her Young ones alive, and has a Matrix like a Bitch, her other parts like a Fiſh; it is the moſt rapacious ſort whatever, eating all ſort of Animals that they can catch; inſomuch, that it is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous going into the Water to Bath, or to fall into the Sea, where-ever they are, for the beſt Swimmer in the World will not be able to eſcape them.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Marſouin,</hi> or Sea-Hog, is the ſame bigneſs as the <hi>Requiem,</hi> and very good Food; theſe will offer no injury to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind. There is Bacon made of them, but of an ill ſavour; their Sides and Intrails are the ſame as in a Swine, excepting that they have two ſeveral Stomachs, one at the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:153719:40"/>of the <hi>Ooſophage,</hi> the other ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joining to its ſide, and near as large as the former. To this is a ſmall paſſage as big as the Pipe of a Quill, by which the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication from the one to the other is perform'd: They are full of little Cells, very like the Cells of a Honey-Comb. The <hi>Duodenum,</hi> I very well remember, has its riſe from the latter. I had not an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to make a juſt ſearch, our Seamen had ſo mangled it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Whales</hi> are prodigious in ſize, both as to length and thickneſs; ſo that they of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſeem to exceed a Veſſel of 26 Tun burthen: However, they never overturn a Ship, nor ſo much as a little Bark or Shallop, <hi>which care of theirs muſt be rather attributed to the thinneſs and tenderneſs of their skin than any good intentions, they not being able to ſtrike againſt any thing that is hard, unleſs when they are wounded, then the Fiſhermen in their Boats muſt keep off at their peril.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Blower</hi> very near reſembles a Whale, but of a much leſſer ſize; they fling up Water as the Whale, but only by one ſingle paſſage, which is above their Muzzel, whereas the others have two.</p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:153719:41"/>
            <p>I do not know the Name of a certain Fiſh, from whoſe Upper-Jaw a Bone ſhoots out the length of four Foot, having ſharp pricks a croſs all along each ſide, rang'd in equal diſtances, and very ſharp; which Weapon they often make uſe of. <hi>This Fiſh we call the</hi> Sword Fiſh, <hi>they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd Enemies to the Whale, and often En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter them with advantage, wounding the Whales at that Rate, that they force them. ſelves aſhore, and bleed to Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are a ſort which the Seamen call <hi>Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tons,</hi> which have a large Bone ſituated in the ſame place as the ſo mer, with thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> difference alone, that 'tis ſmooth and very ſharp. I believe 'tis the ſame we call the <hi>Naruval.</hi> This Bone reſembles the Fabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Horn of the Unicorn. This Fiſh i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> capable of piercing a Veſſel, and making her leak Water; if it does not happen that endeavouring to get clear they brea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this Bone, and then it ſerves for a Peg to mend the hole it made.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sucker,</hi> ſo call'd for fixing them ſelves to any Veſſels by their Mouths, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſucking, they are of the bigneſs of a Sole when they faſten upon the Rudder the retard the Ship, but not ſtop it as is fal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> reported of the <hi>Remoras.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:153719:41"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Amph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ions</hi> Creatures are not frequently met withal upon theſe Coaſts; nor do you often meet with the <hi>Crocodile,</hi> the <hi>Sea-Harſe,</hi> or the <hi>Sea Calf,</hi> the <hi>Lamantin,</hi> and the <hi>Tortoiſe,</hi> unleſs it be at the Mouths of <hi>Senegal</hi> and <hi>Gamby.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are in Marſhes and Pools ſmall <hi>Crocodiles</hi> of about 5 Foot in length, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſome are venomous, and others not They are in the Nature of Serpents, and frequent thoſe places that have moſt plenty of Piſmires. Theſe little Creatures build themſelves a kind of Forts by degrees, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying little Morſels of Earth till they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the Hillock to 12 or 15 Foot in compaſs, being hollow underneath like an Oven, and ſo rang'd, that you wou'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve them at a diſtance to be a Village.</p>
            <p>There are in the River <hi>Gamby</hi> Crocodiles of above 20 Foot in length, and propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionably in thickneſs; inſomuch, that they will ſwallow a Kid whole. They are very dangerous Creatures, having their Tails full as long as the reſt of their Body; their Skin is ſo hard that a <hi>Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gaye</hi> cannot pierce it; ſome of them will Eat nothing but Fiſh, others will venture upon a Man. When they Watch for their Prey, they hide themſelves in ſome frequented Rivers, and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:153719:42"/>being near to any that go Waſh themſelves, or if they are Rowing in a Canoe, or if a Bullock comes thither, they will catch them with their Tails, and ſo devour them; they only move their upper Jaw, their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one being immoveable. They do no great miſchief out of Water; when the <hi>Negers</hi> kill them they eat them. They lay their Eggs on Land, covering them with Sand; when they have done, they return either into the Rivers, or the Woods.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sea-Horſe,</hi> ſuch as are met withal in the <hi>Niger,</hi> is of the bigneſs of an Aſs, and of the ſhape of a Horſe; his Skin is hard, and without hair, and lives on Land as well as in Water, which he never leaves, ſaving when he goes to feed. They make great Havock amongſt the Mill and the Rice, ſince they ſpoil ten times more than they eat. They will overturn the Canoes of the <hi>Negers,</hi> but however they do not ſeize on the Men: They have two large Teeth which is made uſe of as Ivory.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sea-Ox,</hi> which comes and feeds on Land, is as large as a Calf of 6 Months old.</p>
            <p>There are more <hi>Lamantins</hi> in the River of <hi>Senegal</hi> than in that of <hi>Gamby;</hi> they are as large as the <hi>Marſouin,</hi> and have the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:153719:42"/>ſame ſort of Fleſh and Bacon; when they are out of the Water, they make uſe of their Fins inſtead of Feet. This is all that I know of things of this Nature; I ſhall now give you an account of the Manners and Genius of the <hi>Negers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Negers</hi> are very well ſhap'd, and very proportionable in their make and ſize: You ſhall not ſee any amongſt them either Hunch-back'd or Lame, if it does not befal them by ſome miſchance. They are Stupid, and without Addreſs, even in Matters of the ſmalleſt concern: They are ſwinging Liars, but greater Thieves. They have a dexterity in nothing elſe but in Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, having ſo good a knack at this bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, that they will Rob you before your face, without your perceiving any thing of the matter, by ſcraping away with one of their Feet what they have a mind to take, and then taking it up behind them.</p>
            <p>When any of the <hi>Mountaneers,</hi> for ſo they call them that come off from Land, come to Negotiate with us, there is no manner of Cheats but the <hi>Negers</hi> will put upon them; for under pretext of helping them to carry their Merchandiſe, and to be ſerviceable to them in the nature of Interpreters, they will fairly keep half of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:153719:43"/>the value of what they receive from us, as though they had a real intereſt in the Goods.</p>
            <p>The terror of thoſe Puniſhments which their Kings inflict on thoſe who Rob on Nights, and the many Perſons taken in the Fact, cannot remedy this Vice that is ſo Natural to them; notwithſtanding the Chaſtiſement in this caſe is ſufficiently rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, for on this account they are to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Slaves to thoſe whom they have Robb'd.</p>
            <p>Whoever is oblig'd to make uſe of <hi>Negers</hi> for Interpreters, is miſerably expos'd to their Rogueries, they ſcarce ever giving a true account of what is ſpoke, always finding out ſome evaſion that is quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; and by that means often render our Bargains litigious.</p>
            <p>Their Manners are altogether inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable, eſpecially when they believe themſelves to be ſerviceable in any reſpect. Their Drunkenneſs is to an extream exceſs, being continually gorg'd with <hi>Aqua Vitae;</hi> their Palm Wine is not plentiful enough to be always at hand. Their Drunkenneſs is accompanied with a total deprivation of Reaſon, and a furious Brutality.</p>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:153719:43"/>
            <p>They are not ſenſible of what Nature is Reſtitution, nor have they the leaſt tincture of Civility. Their<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ignorance is ſo notorious, that they ſcarce can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend that two and two makes four; nor have they any knowledge of their Age, nor of the days of the Week, for which they want Names to diſtinguiſh.</p>
            <p>Their <hi>Maraboux,</hi> who have ſometimes a ſmall tincture of the <hi>Arabs,</hi> writing their <hi>Griz Griz</hi> in that Language, I ſhall take to explain theſe terms hereafter.</p>
            <p>Theſe People have but one good Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, they are very Hoſpitable; nor do they ever ſuffer a Stranger of their Nation to go from them, without entertaining them with Eating and Drinking, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their beſt to detain them for ſeveral days. And as they ſet their <hi>Aqua Vitae</hi> in great eſteem, they therefore conceal it from their Gueſts, ſince they would be aſham'd not to give it them ſhould it be ſet in view. They recompence them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of their Hoſpitality towards the Mountaneers, by cheating them of the <hi>Aqua Vitae</hi> which they have in exchange for their Merchandiſe, never allowing them ſo much as a half.</p>
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:153719:44"/>
            <p>They are all extreamly Poor, their whole Stock depending on a few Cattle, the moſt Rich not having above 40 or 50, 2 or 3 Horſes, with, perhaps, as many Slaves; 'tis very rare that they have any Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Gold to the value of 11 or 12 Piſtoles.</p>
            <p>Though they have no Wit, or any Talent of a Genius, yet they are exceſſive Lovers of Praiſes and Adulation; ſo that there are a ſort of People call'd <hi>Guiriotz,</hi> whoſe buſineſs it is to perform this piece of Service. Theſe <hi>Guiriotz</hi> carry a ſort of Drums near four or five Feet in length, made of a hollow Trunk of a Tree, which they Beat either with their Hands, or with ſmall Sticks. There are alſo <hi>Moreſque</hi> Drums, reſembling Baskets, croſs'd over with little Cords, which they finger with one Hand whilſt they ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ike with the other.</p>
            <p>I obſerv'd that they made uſe of another ſort of Inſtrument, ſufficiently Harmonious did they know how to touch it; it gives a ſound like a Harp. It conſiſts of a row of ſeveral Strings of ſeveral ſizes, ſuſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the touch like the Wires of a Spinet.</p>
            <p>I ſaw another of their Muſical Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which would be proper for the Chamber of a Sick Perſon. 'Tis a kind of Lute made of a piece of hollow Wood,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:153719:44"/>cover'd with Leather, with two or three Strings of Hair, and adorn'd with Iron Plates and Rings like a <hi>Tambour de B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſque.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Guiriots</hi> Tune theſe ſeveral In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments to their Voice, which is very harſh; and thus they Sing Panegyricks of their Men of the beſt account. The ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Topicks are, that they are great Lords, Rich, and as Puiſſant as the White Men, who are great Slaves of a King; and, in a word, an infinite number of ſuch fooliſh expreſſions.</p>
            <p>Theſe Perſons are Tranſported with their Elogies, and largely recompence theſe <hi>Guiriots,</hi> who Sing their Praiſes. They make their Acknowledgments at ſo great a rate, that I have ſeen them ſtrip themſelves to reward theſe falſe and fulſom Flatteries. When theſe Varlets miſs of their expected Fees they fall a railing, and publiſh in the Villages as many baſe things as they can rip together againſt them, contradicting whatever they had ſaid good of them; which is look'd upon to be the grandeſt Affront imaginable.</p>
            <p>'Tis eſteem'd a very great Honour when the King's <hi>Guiriot</hi> Sings any ones Praiſes, and he never fails of a good Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, they ſometimes giving 2 or 3 Bullocks, and often the beſt part of their Goods.</p>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:153719:45"/>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Guiriots</hi> do not omit the Singing the ſame ſtuff to us, crying, That we are Great, and Rich Lords of the Sea; but they ſcarce find it worth their while amongſt us, ſince we are not ſuch ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Boobies as the <hi>Negers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Habits of the <hi>Blacks</hi> are very plain. The poor People have nothing but a piece of Linnen, or Cotton, of about half a Foot breadth, to cover their Nakedneſs; 'tis faſten'd to a Cord, which ſerves them for a Girdle, and they let the Cloth hang down before and behind them, which they look upon as a great Ornament.</p>
            <p>The Gentlemen, and Men of Quality, are ſomething better Equip'd. They have a Cotton Frock made in the ſhape of a <hi>Franciſcan's</hi> Gown, with long and large Sleeves; they are not Plaited at the Neck, for they only have a ſlit to put through their Heads like a <hi>European</hi> Smock; they have them of all Colours, ſome have blue, yellow, brown, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since theſe Jackets reach but half way down their Thighs, they have Breeches of the ſame Stuff, that reach from the Girdle place below the Knees. Theſe Trowſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s are ſo large, that they take up five Ells of Cloth; they reſemble Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:153719:45"/>Petticoats-Sew'd together at the bottom, leaving only 2 places to put the Legs through; the largeſt are the moſt faſhionable.</p>
            <p>They wear upon their Heads a ſort of Bonnets, ſtreight at the entrance, but large at the bottom, ſomething like the Hood of the <hi>Jac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bins.</hi> The Common People go with their Feet Naked, but the People of Quality have Sandals made of a piece of Leather cut into the Shape of a Shooe Sole, faſten'd at the top of the Foot with Thongs, alter the manner of the Sandals of the Ancients.</p>
            <p>Their Hair, tho' ſhort, yet is treſs'd up very prettily, and adorn'd with <hi>Gris-gris,</hi> Silver, Leather, Coral, Copper, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> They wear at their Ears Rings of Tin, Silver, and Copper. Thoſe that are Born of a Race of Slaves are not allow'd to wear their Hair.</p>
            <p>The Maids and the Women go Naked from the Girdle upwards, unleſs the Cold obliges them to fling over ſome Covering; the other part of their Body they Cloath with a <hi>Paign,</hi> which is a piece of Linnen or Cotton ſtrip'd after their faſhion, about the bigneſs of a Towel, which reaches to the half Leg. Their Hair is alſo deck'd with Coral, and other little Baubles; their Head-Dreſs makes a Creſt upon the Head half a Foot high, the higher they eſteem the handſomer.</p>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:153719:46"/>
            <p>The Girls and the Boys go Naked till Eleven or Twelve Years old. Men and Women adorn their Legs and Arms with Coral, Bracelets of Silver, Gold, Tin, and Copper, according as they abound in Wealth.</p>
            <p>Cotton, with which theſe People Cloath themſelves, would be produc'd amongſt them in abundance would they beſtow labour to Cultivate it; but they content themſelves with what they have a Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and very often want even that. The Women Spin the Cotton, and the Men make the Cloth; nor has their Pieces above five Fingers in breadth, for want of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Employments for the making broader, otherways they would make as good Weavers as in <hi>France.</hi> They are forc'd to join ten or twelve Pieces toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to make a ſmall breadth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mill</hi> is the ordinary ſuſtenance of the Weſtern <hi>Negers;</hi> the Women that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare it make thereof <hi>Sanglet</hi> or <hi>Couſcouſe,</hi> which are their terms that ſignify two man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Victuals.</p>
            <p>They begin at break of day to make their <hi>Sanglet,</hi> for it requires full ſix hours for the preparing it. Two or three go about this Work, then taking all the <hi>Mill</hi>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:153719:46"/>they are to make uſe of at this time, they Pound it in deep Mortars made of Wood, having not the practice of any Mills: When the <hi>Mill</hi> has loſt its Husk; they win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>now it with Fans made of Leaves of Palms to cleanſe it; afterwards they Boil it in Milk, or with Butter, or Meat Broth, or with dry'd Fiſh, or with Water.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Couſcouſe,</hi> which is their beſt Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, is alſo <hi>Mill</hi> well beaten and clean Sifted. When 'tis well cleanſed, a little of it is put in a Bowl, and ſprinkled a little Water upon the Meal. After 'tis well turn'd by Hand, ſome more Water is put in, and then 'tis to be well Moulded again; then 'tis to be made up in little Balls. They are then to be dry'd; when they are well dry'd; they are ſet in a Pot full of holes, upon another Pot where Meat has been Boil'd ſeaſon'd with Selpiment and Palm-Oyl, when any is to be had. This <hi>Ragou</hi> is well enough when 'tis rightly prepar'd, and the Sand well Dreſs'd out; which is ſeldom done.</p>
            <p>When they go to War, they take along with them a little Bag a Foot long, and the thickneſs of a Man's Arm, full of <hi>Couſcouſe</hi> ready Boil'd. Since the Women have this Handy-work for their daily Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:153719:47"/>they are not a little buſied. Should the Women of <hi>France</hi> take ſuch conſtant pains for their Husbands, I fear the Men would lead but ſorry Lives.</p>
            <p>For their Beeverage, they have Palm-Wine, and Water out of ſome ſtinking Ditch, or from a worſe place; they make uſe of Milk when they can get it.</p>
            <p>As Ambition is a Paſſion unknown to theſe People, they give themſelves no trouble of Building Towns, Caſtles, or Houſes of Pleaſure; but however, they have neither Induſtry nor Materials. They Inhabit only in Villages, in Houſes as I have already deſcrib'd. There are ſeveral made according to their Quality or Sufficiency; thoſe that are neareſt the Palm-Trees are the handſomeſt, though they be alſo with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out either Doors or Windows. The Houſe of a great Lord will be compos'd of, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, 30 Pavillions, which they call <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bettes;</hi> ſometimes of 40 or 50. A Poor Man will have but two or three, and the King above a Hundred, but cover'd with Straw as the others.</p>
            <p>Thoſe of Perſons of Quality are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſs'd with Palliſades of either Straw or Thorns propt up with Stakes: Theſe <hi>Combettes</hi> communicate one to the other by
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:153719:47"/>ways laid out in the form of Labyrinths; within the Precincts of the Houſe are very ſine Trees according to the Capacity of the Owner, though they be ſcatter'd, and without any regularity, as the place has by Nature produc'd them.</p>
            <p>The Building of the Palace of King <hi>Damel</hi> ſurpaſſes all the reſt in Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence. Before you come to the Gate of the Palliſades, which makes the firſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſure, there is a ſpacious open Field, where his Horſes are Manag'd, tho' there be not above ten or twelve of them in all. Without, by the ſides of thoſe Palliſades, are the Grand Seigniors Cabbins: You go in from this place into the Palace by a large Avenue; this place is adorn'd with ſeveral Trees which we call <hi>Collbaſſiers,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their Fruit reſembles a <hi>Calbaſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Perſons that are Employ'd the neareſt about the King, have their Cabbins by the ſide of this Avenue; and their nearneſs, or diſtance, from the <hi>Combett</hi>-Royal, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhes their Ranks. Each of their Cabbins are alſo encompaſs'd with Palli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſades; you muſt turn and wind very much before you can come to the King, few Peop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e dare go into his Appartment.</p>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:153719:48"/>
            <p>All the Women have their Lodgings ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parately, and each of them have five or ſix Slaves to ſerve them. The King may Lye with which he pleaſes, without crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a jealouſie in any of them. He has always one whom he loves better than the reſt, and when ever he is weary of her, he diſpatches her into ſome Village with her Slaves, and appoints her Land for her Maintenance. To her ſucceeds another, of 30 which he keeps; the one half of them are ſent away into the Country.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Negers,</hi> from this place to <hi>Gamby,</hi> obſerve the Law of <hi>Mahomet;</hi> but in the Territories towards <hi>Siera Liona,</hi> and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Coaſt of <hi>Gold,</hi> have for the moſt part no Religion at all, or, at leaſt, they Worſhip what they firſt meet withal in the Morning. Formerly they were Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, worſhipping the Devil, to whom they Sacrific'd Bullocks; and though they fed upon Cattel, yet they were Believers of the <hi>Metempſucoſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are ſome who will not have the <hi>Lizards,</hi> which run about their Huts, kill'd, upon any account whatever; for, ſay they, 'tis the Soul of either their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or Mother that comes to make the <hi>Folgar</hi> with them, which is to ſay a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment.</p>
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:153719:48"/>
            <p>They receiv'd their <hi>Mahometan</hi> Religion from the <hi>Azoaghes</hi> or <hi>Arabs,</hi> of whom I have already told you. It is but very pittifully obſerv'd by the vulgar ſort, who are only lightly tainted with it. The ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial are more devour, for they general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have a Mooriſh <hi>Maraboux</hi> that belongs to them, which are cunning Rogues, and have a ſtrong Influence upon them. They make their <hi>Sala,</hi> or Prayers, three times a day, in the Morning towards Sun riſing, towards Noon, and in the Evening; ſome in the Afternoon: The meaner ſort of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſay them not at all, or at leaſt but very ſeldom, nor do not trouble themſelves in the Building of <hi>Moſques.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The King and the Grandees have <hi>Moſques</hi> cover'd with Straw like their other Houſes They there keep ſtanding a conſiderable time, looking againſt the ſide towards the Sun riſing; then they advance two Paces, muttering ſome Words betwixt their Teeth, then they lay themſelves flat upon their Faces, then riſing they place themſelves upon their Knees, making a Circle round about them upon the Earth, and about their Heads two or three ſeveral times. Afterwards they kiſs the Earth by ſeveral <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erks putting Sand upon their Faces with both
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:153719:49"/>Hands, repeating the ſame Ceremonies for the ſpace of half an hour.</p>
            <p>One demands of God Almighty that he may have no Enemy, but ſuch as he has Power to defeat; that God would do him no Injury. Another begs, that he may have handſom Women, and great ſtore of Mill, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> During their Prayers no Accident whatever is capable of Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting them, even though they ſaw their own Houſes in flames.</p>
            <p>They believe Predeſtination, and when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they fall into diſgrace, they charge the Cauſe upon God Almighty; ſo that if one Neger be killed by another, they ſay that God killed him. However they lay hold on the Murtherer and ſell him.</p>
            <p>They are ſo Superſtitious that they ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that having certain Spells, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſo much as touched by any Beaſts that approach them, ſince that will either deſtroy them, or procure them ſome mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance.</p>
            <p>They have a ſort of Character which they call <hi>Gris-gris;</hi> theſe are little Billets of the <hi>Arabian</hi> Character, interlaced with Negromantick Figures, which are ſold them by the <hi>Maraboux.</hi> One ſerves to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent their being Wounded, to help their
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:153719:49"/>ſwimming, to procure them good ſucceſs in their Fiſhing; others for procuring them great ſtore of Women and Children; to hinder their being taken Captive; and in General; for all purpoſes that either Suits with their Fears or Wiſhes.</p>
            <p>They have ſo great an aſſurance in theſe Characters, that ſome of them by their Protection will not ſcruple ſtanding the ſhot of an Arrow. 'Tis true, that they are arm'd wholly over with this Magical Cuiraſe, not one ſingle part of their Body being deſtitute thereof, ſo that they could ſcarce be hurt with a <hi>Zagay.</hi> Their Grand Seignior more particularly have their Veſts and their Bonners wholly covered there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, often loading themſelves at that rate, that they are oblig'd to be ſet on Horſeback. They alſo affix them to their Horſes to render them more ſprightly, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent their being wounded.</p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Gris-gris</hi> are wrap'd up in Linnen very hard, folded and glew'd, and cover'd over with a red Leather handſomly fitted up ſome of them are no larger than your Thumb, worked up and Pointed in form of a Diamond, of which they make Brace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, into which the <hi>Marabouxs</hi> do often encloſe nothing at all; as I have experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:153719:50"/>by ſome that our Slaves wore.</p>
            <p>Before and behind them, at their Back and Stomach, they have them very large as big as a Book in Quarto, and the thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of your two Thumbs; they make them in the ſhape of a Horſes Arſe, of a Stag Horn, or of a Wild Bull, cover'd with red Cloth. Two of this latter ſort they affix to their Bonnets, and in this Equipage they appear very frightful; this ſecures them in their Combats which they have one with another, but not all againſt our Musket-ſhot; ſo that they are accuſtom'd to ſay, that there is no <hi>Gris-gris</hi> that is <hi>Pou</hi> proof, which is the Name they give our Fire-Arms.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Maraboux</hi> ruin them by the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe of this <hi>Gris-gris,</hi> for they make ſome which they ſell for three Slaves, others for four or five Bullocks, according to the ſtock of Vertue or Force which they attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to it. The Opinion the <hi>Negers</hi> enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain for their <hi>Gris-gris,</hi> has impos'd upon the Ignorant of the <hi>French,</hi> ſo that they have believ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d to have met with frequent Sorceries amongſt theſe People. There is a certain time when theſe pretended Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerers make a thouſand Grimaces, Singing or Crying, when, as they ſay, the Devil beats them.</p>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:153719:50"/>
            <p>When they believe that this happens, if it be a Woman they Dreſs her in the Garb of a Man, and put a <hi>Zagay</hi> into her Hand, and walk about Singing with a very mournful and deploring Voice, being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that by this means they ſhall chaſe away the Devil with this Ceremony. I have often obſerv'd, that theſe pretended Witchcrafts have been abſolute Cheats, for when we take Cudgels and belabour well the Perſon ſo poſſeſs'd, this Exorciſm is of ſo great force, that the Devil never returns more.</p>
            <p>During their <hi>Ramadan,</hi> which is the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometan's Lent,</hi> and which continues all the Moon of <hi>September,</hi> they perform the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony of Circumciſion; they ſtay till the Children be ten or twelve years of Age. 'Tis a <hi>Maraboux</hi> that cuts the Prepuce, which muſt be eaten by the Perſon Circumcis'd, who by no means is to complain of any Pain that he ſuffers; nay, they often laugh when they are Seer'd with a Hot Iron for the ſtanching of the Blood.</p>
            <p>So long as the <hi>Ramadan</hi> laſts, they make their <hi>Folgar</hi> in the Night, for during the day time they do not ſo much as eat a ſingle Morſel, nor Drink, nay, not ſo much as Smoak; ſome of them dare not Spit. As
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:153719:51"/>ſoon as the Sun is Set, they make a horri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> noiſe with their Drums, and eat and drink till the day begins to return.</p>
            <p>Though by the Laws of the <hi>Alcoran</hi> they are not allow'd above four Wives, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs they keep as many as they can main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain. As ſoon as they meet with a Laſs that pleaſes them, they demand her of her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; if he conſents to it, they agree of a Price, their Quality or their Beauty makes them inſiſt on high Terms. The Dowry conſiſts of Bullocks, which redound to the benefit of the Father; which Dowry ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver exceeds five Bullocks. This Bargain being made, they Lie together without any farther Ceremony. If they warrant her a Virgin, which is a Commodity very ſcarce in that Country, they lay a white Cloth upon the Bridal Bed, which if it become Bloody, confirms their Opinion of her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Maid.</p>
            <p>Afterwards they walk about the Village, carrying this Cloth in Proceſſion, being accompany'd with ſeveral of the <hi>Cuiriotz.</hi> who Sing the Praiſes of the fair Lady, and their Wedding Joys If on the contrary ſhe does not prove what ſhe was engag'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to be, the Father is oblig'd to take back his Daughter if the Husband requires it, and
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:153719:51"/>reſtore the Bullocks again; though this ſeldom happens, for the Girl is taken un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſtrict Examination before the matter is concluded, nor is the demand made but upon ſure grounds. And if ſhe be reſtor'd, ſhe is not at all ſlighted upon that account, for though ſhe cannot be a Wife but to one, ſhe may be a Concubine to another; and by this the Father has always freſh Markets to make. When, in long run, the Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band is tir'd with his Wife, he drives her away, and may quit her with the loſs of what he gave in Purchaſe; and ſhe her ſelf may take fair leave of her Husband, by reſtoring to him the Bullocks again.</p>
            <p>When the King has a mind to gratify a Favourite, he Preſents him with one of his Women; but this Gentleman cannot upon any terms put her away, though the Prince can retake her whenever he pleaſes.</p>
            <p>The Funerals of the Negroes are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed with great State and Ceremony. A <hi>Marabou</hi> waſhes the Body of the Decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and ſhrouds it up with the beſt Linnen he had during his Life: All the Relations and the Neighbours come to make their Lamentations, asking the Corps ſeveral ridiculous Queſtions. One asks it, if he did not live at caſe with them, what Damage
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:153719:52"/>he had ever done him, if he were not Rich enough to his deſires, if he had a ſufficient ſtore of handſom Women, and other like Fopperies. Seeing he can get nothing in anſwer, he withdraws, and makes room for another, who ſays as much: In the mean time the <hi>Guiriats</hi> do not fail of ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Encomium.</p>
            <p>And ſince it is the Cuſtom to make <hi>Folgar</hi> for all thoſe that come to accompany the Dead; ſome Bullocks are killed for that purpoſe; Slaves are ſold to purchaſe <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> with which they comfort themſelves. When the Aſſiſtants are well feaſted, they inter the Body in the ſame Cabin where he died, taking off the Dome or Covering. At length, whiſſt the Corps is yet above Ground, the Mourners redouble their Yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings; and four People hold a Cloth four ſquare, hiding it that it may not be ſeen.</p>
            <p>Then comes the <hi>Marabou</hi> and whiſpers ſome Words in the Ear of the deceas'd, and covers it with the Pall, and afterwards the Dome is again put on, to which they affix ſome Cloth, either black, red, or any o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her colour ſuitable to their Fancies. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards they erect a Stake, on which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hang the Bow, Quiver, and <hi>Zagay</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Defunct. They ſet by him a Pot
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:153719:52"/>of <hi>Couſcouſe,</hi> and another of Water, which is his Proviſions for a twelve Month, ſince they imagin he can eat though he be dead. In ſome places they encompaſs the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin with Thorns, or a great Trench, to ſecure the Body from Ravenous Beaſts, which however ſometimes do get to it. After this is over, the Mourners con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in their Grimaces for the ſpace of eight days following.</p>
            <p>When 'tis a Boy that is dead, the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and the Girls ſing theſe Funeral Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies, and the Boys run with all the force imaginable one againſt the other, with naked Cimeters in their hands, ruſhing together in the Encounter, claſhing each others Cimeters; upon theſe occaſions they play a hundred fooliſh Pranks, which would be tireſome to relate.</p>
            <p>The Negers have few <hi>Artisans</hi> amongſt them, the moſt common are <hi>Smiths, Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers</hi> and <hi>Potters:</hi> The firſt make Knives, Iron for their Slaves, Rings of Gold, Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, Copper or Iron; trimings for their K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ves and Sebors, and coverings for their <hi>Gri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> They make the Chapes of their Scabbards of what Metal they pleaſe, and the handles of their Sabers. They have no Farriers, ſince they do not ſhoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:153719:53"/>When they are at work at the Forge, they get two or three together under the ſhade of ſome Tree, ſitting upon their Breeches with Pipes in their Mouths: they make ſo little a fire, that you can ſcarce boi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gn Egg at it, which they blow with Bellows made of two Skins, from thence preſſing forth the Wind, which reſembles the ſqueezing of a Bladder. Their Anvil is ſomething like the Stone with which a Mower whets his Sythe, the ſtriking upon which drives it into the Ground, ſo that after every two or three ſtrokes; they muſt pull it out again, which takes up the beſt ſhare of their time.</p>
            <p>Their <hi>Weavers</hi> have but little Employ, for, as I have already mentioned, they make uſe of very few Clouths.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Potters</hi> make but one for of Pots, which ſerve for Kettles, and they make alſo Pipes of which the bole is only of Earth, the ſteal being a ſmall ſtick made hollow, and ſo fix'd to the earthen Head.</p>
            <p>In General, all theſe Handy Craſs Men are intolerably Lazy, and ſpend more than half their time in pratling about Trifles. They are but little concern'd when their Proviſions grow ſhort; for upon this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion they make bold to go Goſſip amongſt their Neighbours.</p>
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:153719:53"/>
            <p>The matter of Huſwifery, except what belongs to eating, gives their Women but little trouble. For the moveables of the greateſt Seignor, amounts to no more than to a few earthen Pots, ſome wooden Uten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſils, and <hi>Calabaſſes</hi> clove in two in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, ſerve for Cups.</p>
            <p>Their Children, thô very ſmall give them but little trouble; for they leave them naked upon the Sand, where they crawl about the whole day: Thoſe which cannot walk themſelves, they carry upon their backs, with their legs to their ſides, bringing their feet before them, and tying them off with a Cloath, which they fix about them.</p>
            <p>Whatever work they do, they keep thoſe Bantlings at their backs, even when they beat their <hi>Millet,</hi> from whence comes that their Bellies are always large, and their Noſes flat; for their Mothers in ſlooping and riſing again by jerks, bruiſe their Noſes againſt their Backs; and ſo theſe Children for avoiding the blows, which however they ſtill meet withal, draw themſelves back, and ſet out their Bellies, which makes them large. I believe this to be the ſole Reaſon that the <hi>Negers</hi> are flat Nos'd and big Bellied. I do not find it true, that they have the greateſt eſteem
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:153719:54"/>for Noſes that are the moſt flat, or for Lips that are the largeſt.</p>
            <p>They have the ſame conſideration for the matter of Beauty as we have, they love a fine Eye, a little Mouth, handſom Lips, and a Noſe proportionable, excepting their black colour. There are Negreſſes as well made as any of our <hi>European</hi> Ladies, they have a better Genius than the Men, and are extreamly ſmooth.</p>
            <p>The Careſſes of White Men pleaſe them wonderfully; but in the mean while, theſe Dames being very Mercenary, they will not grant their favours for nothing. The Men take it for an Honour to have the <hi>Frenchmen</hi> Lye with their Wives, Siſters, or Daughters, they very frequently making the firſt offers.</p>
            <p>It is not the ſame amongſt themſelves, for ſhould this at any time happen, they would certainly Revenge the Fact with either their Sabre or their Knife; however, their Gallantry is not limited to their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubines, whoſe falſeneſs they will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer willingly.</p>
            <p>The Women have always Pipes in their Mouths; they are very brisk and Galliard, and love Dancing in the Evenings, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when the Moon changes. They
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:153719:54"/>Dance in a Ring, clapping their Hands, and not budging from their place, except thoſe in the middle, Singing what next comes in their thoughts, without having any regard either to Rhyme or Senſe. Their latter, in Dancing, hold one Hand upon their Heads, the other upon their Back ſides, thruſting out their Bodies for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, beating their Feet againſt the Earth. Their Poſtures are very Laſcivious and Infamous, eſpecially when a Boy Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with them; a <hi>Calbaſſe,</hi> or a Kettle, ſerves for Muſick, for they are great Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of noiſe.</p>
            <p>The Men Exerciſe themſelves in Wreff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and approach each other in very ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Poſtures, holding up their Finger, Fiſt, or Foot. On theſe occaſions they always have one that plays the part of a <hi>Guiriot,</hi> rattling upon the bottom of a Kettle, or upon a Drum, to excite their Courage; as they are Naked, they have much ado to fling each other upon the Ground. When one is down, the <hi>Guiriot</hi> Sings and extols the Valour of the Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and exhorts the reſt to play their Parts againſt the Champion, better than he that engag'd laſt. They give each other very rude Jolts, and fall very heavy.</p>
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:153719:55"/>
            <p>Moſt of thoſe that live near the Rivers are Fiſhermen, and breed their Children to that Trade whilſt they are very young. They make uſe of Canoes, which are ſmall Boats made of the Trunk of a Tree hollow'd for that purpoſe, all of a piece, the largeſt of which may contain 10 or 12 Men, being 30 Foot in length, and not above two and a half broad. Theſe Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noes go with both Oars and Sails, and they often over-ſet when the Wind is high and the Water rough, tho' they do not much matter it, being all excellent Swimmers, and never ſink to the bottom. They turn it right again with their ſhoulders, and get in as unconcerned as if nothing had befel them, and ſo Row away as ſwift as an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row from a Bow, the nimbleſt of our Shalops not being able to reach them.</p>
            <p>When they go a Fiſhing, generally two of them go into the Canoe, and take a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs near 6 Leagues into the Sea. Their Fiſhing is for the moſt part by Angling, but as there are great Fiſh, which will not bite at the Hook, they ſtrike them with Harping Irons ſomething like broad Arrows, which are fix'd to ſharp Sticks of the length of a Half-Pike, and faſten'd to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e, with which they draw back the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:153719:55"/>Cramping-Iron after they have Darted it.</p>
            <p>They dry their ſmall Fiſh, ſuch as Sprats, and ſlit the large ones ſuch as Green-Fiſh; ſince they do not Salt them, they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ever putrified before they are dry. 'Tis then when they approve of them as the moſt Dainty, not at all eſteeming them whilſt they continue freſh and ſweet. They ſell theſe Fiſh to them who live fartheſt off the Sea, and would thence make a prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious profit, would they give themſelves the trouble to carry it to the Villages; for the Inhabitants are as much too Lazy to come and fetch them, as the other are for carrying them thither, and by their unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable Idleneſs it becomes at length ſpoil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d and good for nothing.</p>
            <p>Beſides the Commerce they have with us, they keep particular Markets amongſt themſelves, but of ſo little conſequence, that I have been amaz'd to ſee them come 6 or 7 Leagues to bring thither a ſmall par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of Cotton, a little Linnen, ſome ſorry Pulſe, as Beans and Fitches, little Wooden Diſhes, and Palm Mats.: Another time I ſaw a Man that had come 6 Leagues to bring a Bar of Iron of half a Foot in length.</p>
            <pb n="106" facs="tcp:153719:56"/>
            <p>Notwithſtanding ſometimes very pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Merchandiſes may be here met with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al; for example, Rings of Gold, Beads for Necklaces, call'd by them <hi>Dougaret,</hi> of the ſame Metal, but theſe are ſo few, that in the whole Market there is not to the value of five Piſtoles. Formerly they us'd to make Exchanges in all their Markets, but ſince their Commerce with the <hi>Europeans</hi> they make uſe of <hi>Raſſade,</hi> and ſmall Baw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels of Glaſs, and little Bars of Iron. What they bring of greateſt conſequence to theſe Markets, which are held at the ends of Villages, are Elephants Teeth, Bullocks Hides, and ſome Slaves; all which they brought to fell at <hi>Goree,</hi> for which the Members of the Company give Iron, Strong Waters, <hi>Raſſade, Indian</hi> Linnen and Coral, by which they reap an unaccoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Advantage.</p>
            <p>Their Government is Monarchical and Hereditary, though they are not the King's Children which ſucceed, but his Nephews, the Sons of his Siſters. This Cuſtom, which however fantaſtical it ſeems, has this for its Ground and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation: That it is not certain whether the Children brought him forth be really his own, but it is inconteſtable that the Sons of
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:153719:56"/>his Siſter are hers, and conſequently more certainly of Royal Blood than his own.</p>
            <p>When the Prince makes his Acceſſion to the Sovereignty, every body comes to Congratulate the Felicity he has obtain'd above the reſt of his Brethren, for general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they being many, the Empire becomes always Conteſted, and falls to him that has the greateſt Force, or the beſt Succeſs.</p>
            <p>None can approach the King without a great deal of trouble and circumſpection, and very few are admitted the Priviledge to ſee the innermoſt Receſſes of his Palace. When a great Lord, even though he be one of his Relations, has procur'd an Audience, he puts off his Frock at the entrance of the Court, being quite Naked from the Girdle upwards. When he draws near the place where the King is, he falls upon the Ground on both Knees. Then he bows down his Head, and with both Hands he often beſprinkles Sand upon his Head and Face, afterwards riſing up, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peating the ſame Ceremony ſtill as he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances from one diſtance to another, till he has reach'd within two Paces of the King. When he is arriv'd ſo near as that; he keeps his Ground, and diſcloſes the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives which he had to demand an Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:153719:57"/>having finiſh'd his Compliment, which is made kneeling, he ariſes without daring to caſt the glance upon the King, reſting his Hands upon his Knees, and from time to time flings. Sand upon his Forehead.</p>
            <p>The Prince very ſlighting of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, ſeems not to regard what was ſaid to him, diverting himſelf ſome other ways; however, he does not omit at the end of the Harangue to anſwer his Demand with an extream affected Gravity, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Supplicant intermingles himſelf with the reſt of the Courtiers that are pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Attendance.</p>
            <p>I believe there are no Princes in the whole Univerſe more Rever'd and more Abſolute than theſe <hi>Neger</hi> Kings; which Deference is an effect of their ſeverity; for upon the leaſt tranſgreſſion of any of their Subjects, at which the King is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleas'd, an Order is immediately iſſued out for taking off their Heads, all their Goods are Conſiſcated, and all their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily made Slaves. The ordinary People are leſs miſerable than the Grandees, being only Subject to Captivity on the like occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</p>
            <pb n="109" facs="tcp:153719:57"/>
            <p>The <hi>Azeaghes,</hi> the <hi>Maraboux,</hi> and the <hi>French,</hi> have a much greater freedom than the <hi>Negers,</hi> and we the greateſt of any, When the <hi>Europeans</hi> accoſt him they make their Reverence, and he reaches out his Hand to be put upon theirs. When this is done, he either ſits or lies according to the Cuſtom of the <hi>Negers,</hi> upon a Bed deck'd with a Quilt cover'd with red Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, having a Pipe in his Mouth. He then makes them ſit down by him, and asks what they have brought along with them.</p>
            <p>Whereas we never have any of theſe Audience but when we are to interceed for ſome favour, or to make Complaints of his Officers, and of Inſults made upon ſome White Men, we never come empty hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; our Preſents conſiſt, for the moſt part in 10 or 12 Pots of Strong-Water, a little parcel of Sugar, ſome Birds Heads, 5 or 6 Ells of Linnen, and ſome pieces of Coral</p>
            <p>When an Envoy has any thing about him which pleaſes the King, as a Coat, Stockins, Shooes, Sword, or Hat, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires to make Tryal of them, I and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ys them on, one after another: This he did, ſoon after we arriv'd, to an Envoy of
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:153719:58"/>Monſieur <hi>Dancourt,</hi> and took from him a Brocade Waſtcoat, his Stockins, Hat and Shooes, ſo that he had return'd to us ſtripp'd Naked, had not he, by good Chance, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken another Suit with him of a leſſer value than the other.</p>
            <p>As long as the Brandy Bottle laſts the Prince is Drunk; thus you muſt expect no Anſwer till it be all off. When he grows Sober he gives his Audience of Congee, preſenting him with two or three Slaves, which he ſends to have taken up in the firſt Villages. Unhappy are they, who at that time fall into the hands of his Guards, for they ſtay to make no Choice, the firſt at hand ſerves the preſent turn.</p>
            <p>Whatever care is taken for carrying Proviſions, when you become a Sollicitor to this Court, yet whilſt you are there you are ready to Dye with Hunger, ſince the King requires your Stock, and for his ſhare does always eat the beſt half. He gives you in Recompence a quarter of a Camel, which is very courſe Food, a little <hi>Couſcouſe,</hi> and ſome Palm-Wine.</p>
            <p>During my ſtay in this Country, a very pleaſant paſſege happen'd, which will ſufficiently diſcover what powerful effects Preſents have upon theſe Princes, and
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:153719:58"/>what ſmall regard they have either to Juſtice or Equity. Two Petty Tributary Kings to <hi>Damel</hi> had a Conteſt about the Succeſſion to a ſorry ſort of Sovereignty; they were Unkle and Nephew; that is, Son of the Deceaſed King, and they main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd their Pretenſions by divers Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments too long, and too frivolous to be here inſerted. They propos'd to terminate their difference either by Force, or by the King's final Judgment. This Prince ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving interdicted all other means, they were oblig'd to refer themſelves to his Deciſion.</p>
            <p>The day being appointed in which Judgment was to be given, the two diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Parties aſſembled themſelves in the great ſpace before the Palace, accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with very numerous Attendance, who form'd two Battalions diſtant from each other about 30 Paces; they were all Arm'd with Darts, Arrows, <hi>Zagayes,</hi> Javelins, and Moreſque Knives. The King follow'd with 600 men Accoutred with their <hi>Gris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gris,</hi> appear'd mounted upon a fine <hi>Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> Horſe, and ſo plac'd himſelf betwixt the two Rivals.</p>
            <p>Though they all ſpoke the ſame Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, yet they made uſe of Interpreters,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:153719:59"/>who repeated to the King what they had heard. The Son of the Deceas'd King finiſh'd his Harangue in demonſtrating; That ſince God had before given thoſe Dominions, which were in Diſpute, to his Father, they muſt of neceſſity belong to him as his Right; and that thus he hop'd from His Majeſty the Confirmation of the Title, which could not be Diſputed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out palpable Injuſtice. The King having hearken'd to him very attentively, told him, with an Air full of Gravity, <hi>God gave it you, and after him I give it you again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such a peremptory Anſwer ſoon diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers'd the Unkles Party, who fairly retir'd by himſelf. The <hi>Guiriots,</hi> with their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments and their Drums, Celebrated the Praiſes of the Victorious, ſaying to him, You Merit this Dignity far beyond the other, and the King has done you nothing but Juſtice: You are by much the finer Man, more Rich, more Potent, and more Valiant, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whilſt this wretched Prince Dream'd of nothing but enjoying his Happineſs, he was wholly ſurpriz'd the day following to ſee himſelf ſtripp'd of this Authority, with which he was but newly Inveſted; for his Unkle not miſſing the opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:153719:59"/>made the King ſo acceptable a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, that it defac'd the remembrance of thoſe he had before receiv'd from the Nephew; ſo that he, in the Morning, diſpoſſeſs'd him that he had Enthron'd in the Evening, and Inſtall'd the other in his place. This Reverſe of Fortune ſoon chang'd the Notes of the <hi>Guiriots,</hi> and they began to Extol him they had before De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry'd. Such is the Perfidy of the Prince, and the Inſtability of his Subjects.</p>
            <p>To return to what concerns the King more particularly, I ſhall tell you, That when he takes the Field, he has no occaſion for Vivandiers, for he is provided for by the Women of the Villages which he paſſes with all his Train. They ſerve him up ſometimes 50 Wooden Platters full of <hi>Couſcouſe,</hi> ſeaſon'd after ſeveral ways, he reſerves which ſuits beſt with his Palate and gives the reſt to his People, who are fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently as hungry after the Repaſt as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>They all eat very naſtily, lying along upon the Ground, taking it up with a full hand, making no uſe of either Napkins or Plates. No body eats with the King but the Grand <hi>Marabou,</hi> or one of the Lords that is moſt Accompliſh'd; often he eats alone.</p>
            <pb n="114" facs="tcp:153719:60"/>
            <p>He will by no means ſuffer the <hi>Thoubabes</hi> (for thus he calls us) to ſee him at his Meals. I believe he conceals himſelf from us, becauſe that he imagines that our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt are more decent and better than his own; and that he is aſham'd of his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty. Amongſt the meaner ſort of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, all of the ſame Family eat together; their firſt Meſs is <hi>Couſcouſe,</hi> when that is clear'd they fall Aboard the Fleſh, which they tear in pieces with their Fingers, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king no uſe of Knives; after they have gnaw'd it, they put it again into the Plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for the next. They uſe only their Right Hand during the Meals, which they always have both at Noon and Night; the Left Hand they reſerve to Work withal, and on that Account they eſteem it an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decency to eat with it.</p>
            <p>The King has under him ſeveral Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of State, who aſſiſt him in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and in the Exerciſe of Juſtice <hi>Condy,</hi> who is a Tributary Sovereign, is after the manner of our Conſtable, and has the General Command of his Troops. The Grand <hi>Geraff</hi> is the Chief Juſtice throughout all the Territories of King <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel;</hi> he goes his Circuits from time to time, to hear the Complaints of all People;
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:153719:60"/>he generally does Juſtice out of hand, and puniſhes a Thief with Slavery; for ſeldom are any People of a private Condition in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with the puniſhment of Death.</p>
            <p>The Kings <hi>Alzair</hi> Exerciſes the ſame Employ as the <hi>Geraff,</hi> but his Power is more limited. He has under him <hi>Alkatys</hi> or <hi>Alkairs</hi> of Grand Villages, that are as particular Lords.</p>
            <p>When a <hi>Neger</hi> is accus'd of a Crime, of which he cannot be eaſily Convicted, he is oblig'd to lick a red hot Iron three ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times; if it burns him he is reputed Guilty, if not, he and his Accuſer leave the Court, and the Proceſs falls without Coſts.</p>
            <p>The Kings of the <hi>Negers</hi> go to War up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on very ſmall pretexts. When any ſuch happens, the <hi>Condy</hi> aſſembles all the great Lords, and the reſt of the Subjects, of which he compoſes his Cavalry, and his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantry. They ſeldom have a body of above twelve or fifteen hundred men; ſo that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir War is but a ſort of a Skirmiſh. In all the Kingdom of <hi>Damel,</hi> they can ſcarce Muſter up together two hundred Horſe. The Men of Quality in the Army, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the Cavalry, are Loaded with their <hi>Gris-gris,</hi> as I have already remark'd. I
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:153719:61"/>believe, ſhould they be once diſmounted, they would no the able to march four paces on foot.</p>
            <p>The Cavalry are armed with <hi>Zagayes,</hi> which is a ſort of a Dart, long and large, with three or four Spears, bigger than thoſe of Arrows, and have ſeveral ſmall Jags, that tears open the Wound when they draw it forth. They can caſt theſe Javelins and <hi>Zagayes</hi> a great way, and go very rarely without them. Beſides theſe they have a Cimeter, and a Moreſque Knife of a Cubit in length, and the breadth of two thumbs. They guard the blows with a round Buckler, made of very thick Leather; though they are thus en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbred, yet they have ſtill their Hands and Arms at liberty, and they can attack very ſmartly.</p>
            <p>The Foot are arm'd with a Simeter, a Javelin, a Quiver ſtock'd with Fifty or Sixty empoiſon'd Arrows, whoſe Wounds are always mortal, if they are not imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately ſeer'd with a hot Iron.</p>
            <p>The Teeth of the Arrows produce ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther miſerable Effect, for they can't be taken out but by another hole which muſt be made by the Arrow it ſelf.</p>
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:153719:61"/>
            <p>Their Bow is made of a Reed, very like that which we call a <hi>Bamboo;</hi> what they make uſe of for the String, is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſort of Wood very curiouſly fitted up. They are ſo dextrous in ſhooting out of Bows, that they will hit a mark of the compaſs of a Crown above Fifty Paces. They march without any order of Diſcipline, even in the Enemy's Country. The <hi>Guiriotz</hi> excite them to Combat by the ſound of their Inſtruments.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as they are within Shot, the Infantry diſcharge their Arrows, and the Cavalry caſt their Javelins. This Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge is follow'd with Blows of the <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gays.</hi> They ſpace their Enemies as much as poſſible, that they may make the more Slaves; the Perſons of Quality them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are not exempted. As they are naked, and very dextrous, their. Wars are very Bloody. They are very hardy and had rather loſe their Lives, than be guilty of the leaſt Cowardice. The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight that is ſhew'd to a, Coward, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, and the fear of loſing their Liberty, does very much augment their Bravery.</p>
            <p>This firſt Shock being over, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin a freſh often for two or three days
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:153719:62"/>together; afterwards they ſend <hi>Marabou</hi> of each ſide to treat of Peace. When they have agreed of the Conditions, they ſwear upon the <hi>Alcoran</hi> and by <hi>Mahomet,</hi> though they know very little of either one or the other. The Priſoners of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide have no Benefit of the Peace, continuing Slaves as though the War were to be Eternal.</p>
            <p>See here in ſhort how Affairs ſtand in this Country. Whatever I can meet withal farther, before my return into <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> I ſhall take a juſt and faithful Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count thereof, that I may diſcharge my ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of what my Friends have enjoyn'd m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which was to communicate to them my O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ervations. My little Knowledge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Writing, and my uncouth Stile, will ſoon diſcover my ſmall Ability of tranſmitting to them theſe Relations. All that can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> pleaded on my behalf, is, that I ſhall no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> impoſe upon them, and that I ſhall give preference to Truth before the Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of diſtinguiſhing my ſelf by a recital more ſtuffed with Singularities, than thoſe of others.</p>
            <trailer>The End of the Firſt Voyage of the Sieur <hi>le Maire.</hi>
            </trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="bookseller_to_the_reader">
            <pb n="119" facs="tcp:153719:62"/>
            <head>The Bookſeller's Advice to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> Particular Perſon that is very knowing, having travelled the Coaſts of <hi>Africa,</hi> and ſeen the Author of this Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age at his Reſidence at <hi>Goree,</hi> remitted to me theſe following Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations. I thought my ſelf ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to publiſh them, and affix them to this, and to acquaint you they are not the Remarks of the Sieur <hi>le Maire.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:153719:63"/>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="121" facs="tcp:153719:63"/>
            <head>Relations of the Iſlands and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacent Places of the Rivers of <hi>Breſalme, Gambie, Zame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nee, St. Domingo, Geve,</hi> and others, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Kingdom of the <hi>Barbeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines,</hi> who are almoſt all Neger <hi>Mahometans,</hi> is very ſmall, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving not above ſix or ſeven Leagues upon the Coaſt: 'Tis joyned to that of the <hi>Joloffes,</hi> beginning at a Village called <hi>Joualle,</hi> ſituated upon the Sea-Coaſts, inhabited by ſome <hi>Mulatters</hi> and <hi>Portugueſe.</hi> There is another ſmall Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage which they call <hi>Coringue,</hi> which is nearer to <hi>Cape-Verd,</hi> and is dependant of <hi>Joualle,</hi> 'tis there they drive the greateſt Commerce.</p>
            <p>In going up about ſeven or eight Leagues we meet with the River <hi>Breſaline,</hi> whoſe
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:153719:64"/>Mouth is very large, filled with ſand Beds, which prevents the Entrance of Conves, Shalops, or little Barques, nor do they drive any great Traffick here, this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom affording no manner of Varieties. However the <hi>Portuguefe</hi> do here paronaſe both Salt and Victuals.</p>
            <p>Upon the ſame Coaſt, two Leagues higher, is the River <hi>Gambie,</hi> which has two Paſſages for Veſſels, the one to the North, and the other to the South, where Ships of Five Hundred Tun may eaſily enter. You muſt firſt ſound the Paſſage with a Shalop, for fear of ſtriking upon the Sands; having entred, you meet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al towards the North the Kingdom of <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra,</hi> whoſe King lives a quarter of a League from Sea. The People and Inhabitants are called <hi>Mandingues,</hi> for the moſt part <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Iſland <hi>Chiens,</hi> to which you may go dry Foot at low Sea, is right over againſt it in the River. The French did formerly inhabit it, but they had their Throats cut by the Negers, afterwards it was not inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited, being of no Conſequence.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Flouppes</hi> Negers, of which I ſhall ſpeak anon, are juſt in the Entrance upon the South Point.</p>
            <pb n="123" facs="tcp:153719:64"/>
            <p>Six Leagues farther up the River to the North, is the Village call'd <hi>Albroda,</hi> where the French had formerly a Warehouſe, The Engliſh have one at a Village call'd <hi>Zeelfray,</hi> which is a League higher on the ſame Shoar.</p>
            <p>They have alſo a Regular Fort in the Iſland over againſt it, which is not above half a quarter of a League about, built up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Cruſty and Gravelly Rock.</p>
            <p>This Fort has above Fifty Pieces of Cannon mounted, which are of no great uſe for want of Men to Manage them; they are forc'd to fetch all their Water and their Wood from the main Land. Theſe are they who have the beſt ſhare of all the Trade that is made up this great Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, which chiefly conſiſts in Neger Slaves, Ivory and Wax. It is Navigable above Two hundred Leagues.</p>
            <div type="description">
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:153719:65"/>
               <head>A Deſcription of the River <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menee.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE River <hi>Zamenee</hi> is Inhabited by many ſort of Negers, thoſe at its Mouth towards the North call themſelves <hi>Floupes,</hi> People extreamly Savage, with whom no Nation have any Commerce. They are all Pagans, having every one his God according to his particular Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; one worſhips a Bullocks Horn, another a Beaſt or a Tree, to whom they Sacrifice according to their manner.</p>
               <p>Their Dreſs is like thoſe of <hi>Cape-Verd,</hi> and the Inhabitants of the River <hi>Gambie,</hi> which conſiſts in a piece of Cotton Cloath, ſtriped according to the Cuſtom of the Country, which barely covers their Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vities.</p>
               <p>They have no Succeſſion of Kings, the moſt abſolute and moſt powerful amongſt them Commands.</p>
               <p>They Cultivate their Land in pretty good Order, which they ſow with Millet and Rice. Their Riches conſiſt in Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ks, Cows and Goats, of which many
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:153719:65"/>have great quantities. They poſſeſs from the River <hi>Gambie</hi> about 6 Leagues into the Land. Their Villages are well Peopled, diſtant from each other about a quarter of a League.</p>
               <p>The Negers, or <hi>Flouppes,</hi> that Inhabit the Mouth of the River towards the South, are Barbarous, and very Cruel; when they can catch any white Men, they give them no manner of Quarter, and they ſay they eat them.</p>
               <p>Theſe are in Poſſeſſion all along the Coaſts to the Village nam'd <hi>Boulol,</hi> which is at the Entrance of the River St. <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingue.</hi> This Coaſt is much better Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled than that of <hi>Gambie.</hi> The Villages are diſtant from each other near two Leagues, and from the Sea about a quarter of a League.</p>
               <p>About ſeven or eight Leagues farther, the Tide makes a little Brook, which goes up to the Town of <hi>Jam,</hi> where ſeveral <hi>Portugueſe</hi> make ſeveral quantities of Wax, which they ſell and traffick by Land at <hi>Gambie</hi> and at <hi>Cacheaux.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The adjacent Countries are inhabited by Negers which are called <hi>Bagnons.</hi> Theſe have a King who lives about 12 or 13 Leagues off Sea.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="description">
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:153719:66"/>
               <head>Deſcription of the River of St. <hi>Domingue.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE River of St. <hi>Domingue</hi> is ſituated from Eaſt to Weſt; it winds above Two hundred Leagues in length; 'tis alſo inhabited by different ſorts of Negers, and by the <hi>Portugueſe,</hi> who have there ſeveral Towns.</p>
               <p>At its Entrance to the North, there is a Fort belonging to the <hi>Portugueſe,</hi> guarded with four Pieces of Cannon, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by a Serjeant and four Soldiers.</p>
               <p>Four Leagues upwards on the ſame Shoar near the Village of <hi>Boulot,</hi> is the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle River <hi>Linguin,</hi> which loſes it ſelf nine or ten Leagues within Land. They are the <hi>Negers Bagnons</hi> that poſſeſs it, and cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivate the Lands. They are all Idolaters, and worſhip Foreſts or great Woods, and in them many Thieves, whom they ſtand in great dread of.</p>
               <p>The Village of <hi>Quongain</hi> is directly at its Entrance, where abundance of <hi>Portugueſe</hi> and <hi>Gourmets</hi> inhabit, who make there great ſtore of Wax.</p>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:153719:66"/>
               <p>The River <hi>Bougind</hi> is on the ſame Coaſt, about three Leagues beyond where the Tide comes, which diſperſes it ſelf twelve or fifteen Leagues within Land, inhabited by the ſame ſort of People, who as I have told you, traffick altogether with Wax. 'Tis the ordinary paſſage to go from <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choar</hi> to <hi>Jam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At the Entrance of the River St. <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingue,</hi> on the South, is a large Wood, which they call <hi>Matteformoſe:</hi> 'Tis a Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage inhabited by the <hi>Flouppes,</hi> more fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar than thoſe I before mentioned, with whom they traffick for Slaves and Victuals; above all they have great ſtore of Rice.</p>
               <p>Going up the River about two Leagues, you meet with a ſmall River which is not Navigable, which ſeparates the <hi>Flouppes</hi> from the <hi>Papels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Papels</hi> are alſo Heathen Negers, all Idolaters as the former. They have a King who dwells about five or ſix Leagues from them. When any Conſiderable Perſon dies, they Sacrifice Bullocks, Cows, Kids, and Capons to their Gods, who are for the moſt part one or more Trees, or a Bullocks Horn, or ſuch like things.</p>
               <p>In the ſame diſtrict, about four Leagues higher, you meet with the Town called
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:153719:67"/>
                  <hi>Cacheau,</hi> in poſſeſſion of the <hi>Portugueſe,</hi> who have there three Forts, the chief of which may have about ten or twelve Pieces of Cannon, and the other two, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout two or three each. A Captain-Major has the Government, who depends upon the Governor of the Iſlands of <hi>Cap-Verd.</hi> They are every year Recruited with thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or forty <hi>Portugueſe</hi> Soldiers, who are generally baniſhed Criminals, they ſupply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Places of thoſe who die for want of good Nouriſhment, by Neceſſity, or by an over addicting themſelves to Women. 'Tis for them a ſort of Exile, which how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is ſomewhat ſupportable They may have in the Town two or three hundred Inhabitants; the generality of them are <hi>Mulaters,</hi> the reſt are their Wives and Concubines.</p>
               <p>There is in the Town a Receiver of the King's Cuſtoms, from the Ships that come to Traffick there, who pay ten <hi>per Cent.</hi> both coming in and going out, together with a Writer, who holds the Place of both Notary and Sheriff. 'Tis the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor that renders Juſtice. There is alſo a Parochial Church, a Curat, and a Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tator, who is in the nature of Vicar in <hi>France,</hi> who always makes Viſitations on
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:153719:67"/>behalf of the Biſhop of Saint <hi>James.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is alſo a Convent of <hi>Capuchins,</hi> where there are ſeldom more than three or four Religious.</p>
               <p>The Inhabitants of the Town have little Boats and Barks, with which they Negoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate upon the River <hi>Nounne Pougues Serlianne,</hi> and in the Iſland of <hi>Bezagotts,</hi> where they have great Commerce of Wax, Slaves, and ſome ſmall Parcels of Ivory.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Portugueſe</hi> have yet another Town higher up the River, diſtant from <hi>Cacheau</hi> about a Hundred and Fifty Leagues, which is called <hi>Farim,</hi> which is encompaſſed with Pallaſadoes; the Inhabitants are not ſo numerous as in <hi>Cacheau:</hi> Thoſe of the beſt repute in <hi>Cacheau</hi> have alſo Houſes there, where their <hi>Gourmets</hi> make their Cloath and Wax. There is alſo a Curat, a Captain Major, who is depending of <hi>Cacheau.</hi> The Negers who inhabit the the Lands adjacent are called <hi>Mandingues.</hi> All the Villages that are from <hi>Cacheau</hi> to <hi>Farim,</hi> are inhabited by the <hi>Gourmets</hi> of the <hi>Portugueſe,</hi> who gather Cotton, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Leaving the River Saint <hi>Domingue,</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Southwards you meet with ſeveral Iſlands. The firſt is called <hi>Three Iſlands,</hi> which effectively has that Figure, poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:153719:68"/>by the <hi>Gourmets,</hi> or <hi>Negers,</hi> who have loos'd themſelves from the ſlavery of the <hi>Portugueſe,</hi> moſt of them, thô they are Baptiz'd, have renounc'd the Catholick Faith. They Cultivate this Iſland, which produces good ſtore of Cotton, of which they make their Cloath. They have Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noes to ſerve them in their Traffick with the Negers of the Continent. The place which they paſs is called the <hi>Bot;</hi> they have a particular care in ſuffering any Boat to approach their Iſland.</p>
               <p>Over againſt it is the Iſland of <hi>Buſſi<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> in poſſeſſion of the <hi>Papels,</hi> who have a King not very abſolute. It is ſo low Water, that it may be paſs'd by being only wet to the middle Leg.</p>
               <p>It is difficult to Negotiate with them without being known, for their ſtrange miſtruſt makes them ſuppoſe that there is no ſincerity.</p>
               <p>I know that ſeveral Engliſh and Dutch, have been there Maſſacred, for endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to have Commerce with them. They have great Store of Proviſions, as Cattle, Poultry, Wax, Mill and Feaſants, but of a very indifferent reliſh.</p>
               <p>Their Iſland is about ten Leagues in Circuit, and has two Ports, the one to the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:153719:68"/>Eaſt, which is called <hi>Old Port,</hi> the other to the South-Eaſt, which is called the Port of the <hi>White Stones.</hi> Right over againſt it, is the Village of <hi>Cazelut,</hi> and many ſmall Iſlands which are not inhabited. Very near it you find the Iſland of <hi>Biſſeaux</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout two Leagues diſtant. A Veſſel of three hundred Tun may paſs betwixt them both, ſo that the Chanel is well known. It is forty Leagues in Compaſs; the <hi>Papel Negers</hi> which inhabit it are altogether Heathens There are in this Iſland nine Kings, of which one is ſuperior to the other Eight, which properly are no more than Governors of Provinces.</p>
               <p>When any of the Kings die, they take care to ſtrangle more than thirty Perſons, above all the young Girls and the Slaves that have been the moſt faithful to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed, whom they bury along with them. They put with him into his Tomb all his Riches, as his Gold, Silver, Amber Gris, Stuffs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When they chuſe another 'tis after this manner, they are only the <hi>Geagres</hi> that make Pretenſions. which are, as I may ſay, the Dukes and Peers of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They aſſemble together in a Ring, in the middle of which is the Tomb of the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:153719:69"/>deceaſed King, made of Reeds and very light Wood, which is ſuſtain'd in the Air by ſeveral Negers, which they toſs up into the Air, and on whom ever it falls, they chuſe him for King in the Place of the Deceaſed.</p>
               <p>They often Sacrifice to their Gods, Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locks, Capons and Kids.</p>
               <p>There are ſeveral Ports in this Iſland, the chief of which is called Part <hi>Biſſeaux,</hi> Ships of Sixty Guns can there ride at An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor with eaſe.</p>
               <p>The King's Palace is diſtant from thence only half a League there is one Pariſh, and a Convent of <hi>Capuchins,</hi> ſeveral of the <hi>Portugueſe</hi> are married to the <hi>Negreſſes</hi> of the Country.</p>
               <p>There are ſeveral of thoſe Heathens Sons who have received Baptiſm, and embrace the Catholick Faith. The King has his Guards, his Army, and ſeveral Women kind of all Ages. He has about Fifty Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noes of War, which hold about thirty Men; for their Weapons, they have only a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meter hanging at their Arms, and are cloath'd with only the Skin of a Kid, which hangs down behind, and is faſtned up before betwixt the Legs to hide their Nudities. They go to War againſt the
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:153719:69"/>
                  <hi>Biaffores,</hi> who inhabited the Continent, twice or thrice each Year.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Portugueſe</hi> did formerly build a Fort of eight Pieces of Cannon, to hinder Strangers from trading thither, but the Negers would not ſuffer it. They always were ſticklers for the Freedom of their Country, which occaſions a welcom to all manner of Strangers, that come to Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick in their Ports, who may Negotiate in the Iſland with all imaginable Security, without dreading any Inſult. When you arrive at their Port, you have not liberty to ſet foot on Shore, till their King has kill'd a Bullock, and ſacrificed; when he has finiſhed, you have liberty to diſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bark.</p>
               <p>Over againſt the Port is an Iſland call'd <hi>Sortiere,</hi> full of Trees, where the Negers make their grand Sacrifices every year, in which the King himſelf aſſiſts. Veſſels Anchor there very ſafely.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="description">
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:153719:70"/>
               <head>A Deſcription of the River <hi>Geve.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE River <hi>Geve</hi> winds about ſeventy Leagues into the Continent, lying North-Eaſt, South-Weſt. All the Villages of each ſide, diſtant about a League from Sea, are inhabited with the <hi>Biaffares.</hi> At the Entrance of the River towards the North, is the Village call'd <hi>Gouffode,</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant one League from the Port. There it is where Bullocks and Poultry is to be ſold, and they alſo Traffick for ſome Slaves and Ivory.</p>
               <p>Upon the ſame River, five Leagues more upwards, is the Town of <hi>Geve,</hi> the greateſt part of which is poſſeſs'd by the <hi>Portugueſe</hi> and by the <hi>Gourmetts,</hi> which is encompaſſed with Paliſadoes.</p>
               <p>They have one Parochial Church, one Curat, and one Captain, who has the Command, and is dependant on the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor of <hi>Cacheau.</hi> The adjacent Places are poſſeſs'd by the Negers <hi>Biaffares.</hi> Moſt of the <hi>Portugueſe</hi> have Barks in the Port, by which they Trade to <hi>Serlienne.</hi> Cocters is a Fruit which both in ſhape and taſte reſembles the <hi>Marons</hi> of <hi>India;</hi> there are
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:153719:70"/>both white and red, of which they have great trading amongſt them, eſpecially in the Countries of the <hi>Biaffares</hi> and <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingues:</hi> They alſo ſend their Barks to the Negers upon the River <hi>Nounne</hi> for <hi>Morſil</hi> and <hi>Indigo</hi> in leaf, with which they colour their Cloaths.</p>
               <p>The Barks can get no higher than the River <hi>Gowe.</hi> As for their Canoes, they go up ſeveral little Rivers of ſmall Note: You meet with ſeveral Iſlands about the Port, eſpecially that of <hi>Boulam,</hi> well ſtock'd with Trees; 'tis about ſix Leagues in Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit; it is juſt at the Entrance of the River <hi>Riogrando,</hi> and is not at all inhabited. The other Iſlands are of ſo ſmall a Conſequence, that I do not think it worth while to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite them. I will not ſpeak of <hi>Cap-Verd,</hi> nor of the <hi>Canaries,</hi> nor of <hi>Senegal,</hi> ſince the Sieur <hi>le Maire,</hi> by the Care of Mr. <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>court,</hi> has ſaid more than I am capable of ſaying.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb n="136" facs="tcp:153719:71"/>
            <head>Plays Sold by <hi>T. Chapman.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>SOphonisba. By Mr. <hi>Lee.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Theodoſius. By Mr. <hi>Lee.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Oedipus. By Mr. <hi>Dryden</hi> and Mr. <hi>Loe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Country-Wife. By Mr. <hi>Crown.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Abdelazer. By Mrs. <hi>Behn.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ibrahim. By Mr. <hi>Settle.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Heir of Morocco. By Mr. <hi>Settle.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Paſtor Fido.</hi> By Mr. <hi>Settle.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Dryden</hi>'s Plays, in Three Volumes, or Single.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Ottway</hi>'s Plays, Bound or Single.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Lee</hi>'s Plays, Bound or Single.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Shadwell</hi>'s Plays, Bound or Single.</item>
               <item>With Plays of all ſorts.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:153719:71"/>
            <head>Books Printed for <hi>T. Chapman.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Commentaries. By <hi>Edmonds.</hi> with Additions.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi>'s Morals.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Kettlewell</hi> on the Sacrament.</item>
               <item>Fire of the Altar. By Dr. <hi>Horneck.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:153719:72"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153719:72"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153719:73" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153719:73"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
